good night everyone
各位來賓晚安
speech is about to start
演講即將開始
Please set your phone to vibrate or elite
請將您的手機調味震動或精英
speech in progress
演講進行中
Do not take photos with flash
請勿使用閃光燈拍照
Thank you for your cooperation
謝謝您的配合
Ladies and gentlemen, hello everyone
各位女士 各位先生 大家好
I am the deputy executive secretary of the Academic Advisory Council of Academia Sinica
我是中央研究院學術諮詢總會的副執行秘書
My name is Li Chaohuang
我叫李超皇
So the poster was supposed to say
那麼海報上本來寫的是
Today is hosted by Vice President Zhou Meiyin
今天是由周美寅副院長主持
But I'm sorry because the vice president
但是很抱歉 因為副院長他
Temporarily have this overseas itinerary
臨時有這個國外的行程
there is no way to get back
還沒有辦法趕回來
So today I will help him host
所以有今天就我來幫他主持
Then if you become a fan of Vice President Zhou again
那如果再做有這個周副院長的粉絲的話
first say sorry
先跟大家說抱歉
so thank you all very much tonight
那非常感謝大家今天晚上
Use this time after school to attend
利用這個放學下班的時間來參加
our show
我們節目
Feast of Knowledge held by the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
中醫院舉辦的知識饗宴
Well, we have held this event many times
那麼這個活動我們已經舉辦了非常多次
Also accumulated a lot of interesting this
也累積了很多有趣的這個
Some articles on popular science
科普方面的一些文章
Well, there are books outside our collection of articles from previous knowledge feasts
那麼外面有我們歷屆這個知識饗宴的文章集結的書籍
So if you are interested, you can also buy it
所以如果大家有興趣也可以購買
Well, what we are talking about today is actually quite a life-like technology.
那今天我們講的這個其實是相當生活化的科技
Although it has a lot of basic research elements in it
雖然它有非常多的基礎研究的成分在裡面
But the title is a word I think everyone has heard of Thermoelectric Technology
但是title是一個我想大家都聽過就是熱電科技
That is simply how to convert heat into electricity
那簡單的講就是怎麼把熱變成電
Because we know a lot of this energy
因為我們知道很多很多的這個能源呢
It's used then last because the efficiency is not 100%
它的使用那麼最後因為效率不是百分之百
So in the end it's all in the form of waste heat
所以最後都是以廢熱的形式
into our rooms or into the atmosphere
排到我們的房間中或者是排到大氣中
or drain into the water
或者是排到水中
Then these heats are okay
那麼這些熱都是可以
energy used
利用的能源
But, the problem is that it's not easy to collect
但是呢 問題是這很不容易收集
because it's going to be like all kinds of
因為它會到像各種
That is to say, from high temperature to low temperature to diverge
就是說 由高溫往低溫的地方去發散
So the development of thermoelectric technology is in
那麼所以熱電科技的發展在
How can we improve energy efficiency now
我們現在怎麼提升能源的使用效率
how to improve the earth
怎麼改善這個地球
Energy consumption is a very, very
對能源的消耗是一個非常非常
Issues in the spotlight
受到注目的議題
Then we are very honored to have this today
那我們今天非常榮幸請到這個
Our Institute of Atomic and Molecular Sciences, Academia Sinica
我們中研院原子與分子科學研究所的
Director Chen Guixian is here to introduce this
陳貴賢所長來跟大家介紹這個
very important technology
非常重要的科技
Then let me briefly introduce Director Chen Guixian
那我簡單介紹一下陳貴賢所長
In fact, I've known him for probably over 20 years.
事實上我跟他認識大概也超過20年了
I don't know if there are 30 years
不知道有沒有30年
That's definitely over 20 years
那是絕對超過20年
Director Chen is
那陳所長他是
Graduated from the Department of Electrical Engineering, National Taiwan University in 1970
民國70年在台大電機系畢業
That
那
The BA of the big TV drama should have started a business at that time
大電戲BA應該當時要去創業
It's right to be a tech upstart
做這個科技新貴才對
However, Director Chen, because of his interest in science
不過陳所長他因為對科學的愛好
so he went to harvard
所以他就前往哈佛大學
Then earned a Ph.D. in 1989
然後於1989年獲得博士學位
Then he did this
那麼隨後他是做這個
Doing this man-made diamond research at that singular company
在那個奇異公司做這個人造鑽石的研究
Should be very promising
應該也非常有前景
I don't know why he changed his career again
不知道為什麼他又改行
Director Chen is obviously quite persistent in academics
陳所長顯然對學術有相當的執著
Then in 1993 he returned to China to serve
那麼1993年他回國服務
joined the Institute of Atomic and Molecular Sciences
就加入了這個原子分子科學研究所
The way from this research assistant to
那一路從這個助研究員做到
Bitcoin researcher Na is also the director
特幣研究員那目前也是所長
So based on what I know of him
所以以我對他的認識
I think Director Chen is one
我覺得陳所長就是一個
a scientist forever
永遠向前的一個科學家
because when i knew him
因為我認識他的時候
he is still very young
他還是個很年輕
very dark hair
頭髮非常黑
Since then we have seen
那從那個時候開始我們就看到
At that time we will call him Mr. Chen
那時候我們就要叫他陳老師啦
He just has always been able to offer his unique perspective on a variety of issues
他就是一直對各種議題都可以提出他獨到的看法
And keep producing this very creative
然後一直產出這個非常有創意
And there are groundbreaking research results
而且有突破性的研究成果
Then I think in an environment like Academia Sinica
那我覺得在中央研究院這樣的環境
It is a place that complements such good scientists
是跟這麼好的科學家是一個相輔相成的一個場所
We see how good scientists grow
我們看到好的科學家怎麼成長
Then we see good scientists like this
然後我們看到這樣子的好的科學家
Why did you go back and contribute to Academia Sinica?
怎麼又回過頭來貢獻中央研究院
Director Chen is a very, very successful example
這個陳所長是一個非常非常成功的例子
OK, then I'll introduce it here
好 那我就介紹到這邊
Then we will hand over the time to Mr. Chen Gui, the director
那接下來我們把時間交給陳貴先生所長
please applaud everyone thank you
請大家掌聲歡迎 謝謝
ok thank you host for this
好 謝謝主持人的這個
flatter me
幫我吹捧
i think everyone knows
我想大家知道
He is special in several institutes
他是在幾個所比較特殊的
We have the original institute, the mathematics institute and the astronomy institute
我們有原本所,有數學所跟天文所
It's on the campus of National Taiwan University
是在台大的校園裡面
So this has
所以呢 這個有
Although I often come back to the courtyard for meetings
雖然說常常會回來院裡面開會了
But it's my first time to speak here
不過回來這裡演講還是我第一次
The one that the host didn't introduce just now
那個剛剛主持人沒有介紹到的
In addition to graduating from the Department of Electrical Engineering, I went to the United States to study
我除了從電機系畢業後來去美國念書
I think the more exciting part of life
我覺得人生裡面比較精彩的部分
It was the years when I came back
是我回來那幾年
At that time, our Taiwan happened to be from that
剛好那個時候我們台灣剛好從那個
at the time of national transition
民族轉型的時候
There used to be only three TVs
以前電視只有三台
Then there are only seven newspapers
然後報紙只有七家
no more
不能再有其他的
Then we have been going everywhere to demand that the party and government
那我們一直到處去要求這個黨政
have your own voice, your own what
要有自己的聲音自己的什麼
Why was there a so-called underground radio station for a while?
那為搞過一陣子所謂的地下電台
get it up from the ground
從地下把它搞到地上來
There are several home appliances in Taiwan now
現在台灣有好幾家電
The radio station was founded by me
廣播電台是本人創辦的
And then also in public television
那後來也參與了公共電視
Including Hakka TV
包括客家電視
But this is all related to today's theme
不過這個都跟今天的主題
Today's topic is
今天主題是
What I'm going to tell you today is thermoelectric technology
今天跟大家講的叫做熱電科技
heat into electricity or electricity into heat
就是熱轉成電或電轉成熱
Turning electricity into heat is easy, right?
電轉成熱很簡單對不對
Let's pass the current through any light bulb
我們隨便燈泡把電流通過
Cook it hot
電煮它就會發熱
But it turns electricity into heat
不過它這個電轉成熱
It can also convert electricity into energy
它也可以把電變成能
wait a minute i can introduce you
等一下我可以跟大家介紹
It's more difficult to get things down
要把東西能下來是比較難的
English it is called
英文它叫
It's a direct flip with this thermoelectric
就是跟這個熱電直接翻了
Then I want to tell you today
那我今天要跟大家講說
from some of its applications
從它的一些應用
it can be taken from the refrigerator at home
它可以從家裡面的冰箱
communication even to space
甚至到太空的通信
Some history of these past developments
這些過去所發展的一些歷史
the whole outline for today
那今天的整個提綱
right from the beginning of it
就從它的開始
Motivation
Motivation
how did it start
怎麼開始的
and then from its past development history
然後從它過去發展的歷史
And then what we're going to bump into is to discuss
然後我們會碰到的就是要討論
That is to say, what kind of difficulties did it encounter?
就是說它有碰到什麼樣的困難
what chance
還有什麼樣的機會
how to solve the difficulty
困難要怎麼解決
Everyone is still working hard
大家都還在繼續努力
then to the conclusion
然後到結論
This was the beginning of everyone's idea
這個本來大家的構想開始
just want to say
就是想說
we are in many
我們在很多
We are called ICE
我們叫做 ICE
internal combustion engine
就是內燃機
After the Industrial Revolution, machines replaced ordinary animals or humans
工業革命以後機器取代了一般的動物或人力
The most important thing about the machine is that it never cares whether you are burning coal
那機器最重要就是從不管你是燒煤礦
Either burn oil or burn natural gas
或者是燒油或者燒天然氣
You call these oil charcoal or Fast or Fuel
你把這些我們叫油炭或者說Fast or Fuel
These fossils that we live under the ground
我們存在地底下的這些化石
Fast or Fuel should be translated like this
Fast or Fuel應該是這樣的翻譯
You burn it to generate heat
你把它燒了以後產生熱
Then after it is hot, it pushes the engine of the machine
然後熱以後就推動了引擎機器的
But if you review it
但是你如果去檢討它的時候
You will find that a lot of heat is generated after you burn
你會發現說你燒了以後產生了很多的熱
But maybe only 25% 30% are actually used to do what you want to do
但是可能只有25% 30%真正拿去做你要做的事情
most of that
那大部分
More than 60 percent of the heat in this part is wasted
這部分的熱超過百分之六十是浪費掉的
It's hard for everyone to imagine
大家很難想像
say you drive a car
譬如說你開一輛汽車
or drive a motorcycle
或者是開一個摩托車
Actually all the same
其實都一樣
look at that car
你看那個汽車
car it doesn't just say
汽車它不只是說
it moves it smokes
它會動 它會排煙
You need one more in your car
你汽車裡面你還需要一個
we call cooling water
我們叫冷卻水
our radiate
我們那個radiate
what is our chinese name
我們中文叫什麼
three
三個
radiate is not
radiate的不是
radiate is
radiate的就是
We have a cooled front of the car
我們的汽車前面有一個冷卻的
cooling
散熱
water fragrance
水香
water fragrance is
水香就是
Then why the perfume
那為什麼要那個水香
it's your eyes that are too hot
就是你的眼睛太熱了
so you have to cool it with water
所以你要用水去冷卻它
since you are hot
那你既然有熱
why do you want to water it
你為什麼要把它弄水
cool it down drain it
把它冷卻 把它排掉
isn't this a waste
這不是很浪費嗎
In fact it means
事實上就是說
After our gasoline goes to burn
我們的汽油去燃燒了以後
Mostly more than 60%
大部分超過60%
is scattered
是散掉的
Only 30% of them help us work
只有30%之內的幫我們做工
the engine is running
引擎在動
so what
所以呢
If we understand such a situation in the future
如果我們了解這樣的一個情況以後
someone wants to say
馬上就有人想說
Wow, this one is still 60% hot
哇 那這個還有60%的熱
let's make good use of it
我們就好好的利用它嘛
then i remember when i was young
那我記得我小時候
Sitting on the mountain in Nantou
坐在那個南投的山上
they have that iron bullock cart
他們有那個鐵牛車
drive very slowly
開得很慢
Iron ox carts also burn oil
鐵牛車也是一樣的燒油
see you diesel or something
看你是柴油或什麼
that water
那個水
Cool water burns hot
冷卻的水就燒得很熱
So people will be in the cooling water
所以人家會在冷卻水裡面
put some eggs in there
放幾顆蛋在那裡
then at noon
然後到中午的時候
only eggs to eat
只有蛋可以吃了
that might be a
那可能是一種
Flying fish hot for reuse
飛魚熱拿來再利用
After all, it is limited
畢竟是有限
Most of the heat is still dissipated
大部分的熱還是排掉了
so what
所以呢
Many people wanted to say
當初就很多人想說
If I take this heat and find a way to recycle it
我如果把這個熱想辦法把它回收
That
那
Suppose you are sixty percent
假設你是百分之六十
It would be nice if my efficiency was even 10 percent
我的效率如果甚至是百分之十好了
Then I can recycle 6% back
那我還可以回收百分之六回來
that's a lot
那就不少了
so what
所以呢
a lot of research
很多研究
that's just right
那剛好呢
thermoelectric
熱電
because it's hot
因為它有熱嘛
right
對不對
If this heat is converted into electricity
如果把這個熱轉換成電的話
that would be perfect
那就太完美了
So it's not really a new topic
所以其實也不是很新的議題
for example
譬如說
This German BMW
這個德國的BMW
we are bmw
我們叫寶馬
they used to do
他們曾經做過
that is
就是說
thermoelectric material
把熱電的材料
put it on the face of this engine
把它放在這個引擎的表面
or that exhaust pipe
或者是那個排氣管
exhaust pipe is hot
排氣管很燙
look at that motorcycle
你看那個摩托車
The exhaust pipes have to be covered.
排氣管都還要遮起來
you accidentally get burned
你不小心會被燙到
You take this thermoelectric material
你把這個熱電的材料
stick it on
把它貼在上面
it's ok
它可以了
Save about 5% to 10% on gasoline
節省大概5%到10%的汽油
General Motors GM of America
美國的通用汽車GM
It also added a 350 watt thermoelectric system later
它也加了一個350瓦的熱電系統以後
it found that
它發現說
The mileage of this car can be increased by 3%-4%
這個汽車的里程數可以增加3%-4%
That
那
Although
雖然
3%-4% or this saves 5%-10%
3%-4%或者是說這個節省個5%-10%
sounds small
聽起來很小
But what if you say
但是呢你如果說
This every car we
這個每一輛車我們
The world produces tens of millions of cars every year
這個全世界每一年產生千萬輛車
Save this on every car
每輛車都省個這個下來
In fact, it is still very impressive
其實還是非常的可觀
That
那
Then we have to ask why there is no such thing in the cars we buy today.
那就要問說為什麼到今天我們買的車都沒有這個東西呢
we will come
我們就來
Let's discuss
跟大家來討論
That's because such a
那因為這樣的一個
this thought
這個發想
we are at
我們在
A hospital of traditional Chinese medicine started a called
中醫院就開始的一個叫做
Thermoelectric Research Program
熱電研究的計畫
what about this plan
這個計畫呢
from
從
Fate
緣分所
and the Institute of Physics
還有物理所
Fate Institute, except that I am the general convener
緣分所除了我自己是當總召集人以外
Our current deputy chief Wei Jinming
我們現在的副首長魏金銘
turn out to be
原來
This one is Vice President Zhou Meiyin
這一位呢是周美銀副院長
After becoming the vice president
當了副院長以後
I just want to say that I don't want to ask for a referee
就想說不要求援監裁判
So he hastened to give
所以他就趕快讓給
a young
一位年輕的
Wei Jinming
魏金銘
our current deputy chief
我們現在的副首長
in the physics institute
在物理所呢
have
有
Chen Yangyuan
陳陽元
Also former Deputy Chief
也是前副首長
Dr. Chen Yangyuan
陳陽元博士
And Dr. Wu Maokun
還有吳茂坤博士
Academician Wu Maokun
吳茂坤院士
There is another one who is our Indian nationality
還有另外一位呢是我們印度籍的
called Sankar
叫做Sankar
Infection
Sankaraman
sorry
對不起
That
那
Speaking of
講到
Dr. Chen Yangyuan, of course, everyone should
這個陳陽元博士當然大家應該都
He's no stranger, he's more senior than me
他不陌生 他是比我更資深
About ten years ago, I started to do research on thermoelectricity
大概十幾年前 就開始做熱電相關的研究
It's also because of him that I dare to say
也是因為有他 所以我才敢說
Alright then let's get the House team together
好 那我們就好好來把眾議院的團隊給組起來
Academician Wu Zhaokun, you don’t need my introduction
吳昭昆院士 大家就不用我介紹了
He became very famous because of these things in the Ministry of Education a while ago.
因為前一陣子教育部的這些事情 他變得很出名
In fact he was before the Ministry of Education, he was actually more famous
事實上 他在教育部之前 他其實是更出名
Everyone knows this superconductor
大家知道這個 超導體
We have a scientific community, we talk about high-temperature superconductivity
我們有一個科學界 我們講說高溫超導
That is to say, the previous superconductivity had to reach almost this absolute zero.
就是說以前的超導都要到幾乎這個絕對零度
Ten degrees below absolute zero will produce superconductivity anyway
絕對零度的十度以下 才會反正 產生超導
Academician Wu Zhaokun and his teacher Zhu Jinwu
吳昭昆院士 他跟當初他的老師朱金武
In the United States, Houston at that time
在美國,Houston那個時候
One material they discovered is called YBCO
他們發現的一個材料叫做YBCO
four elements together
四個元素合起來
Then raise the temperature of this superconductor to an absolute temperature of 90 degrees
然後把這個超導的溫度提升到絕對溫度90幾度
If I remember correctly, I just know
如果沒有記錯,我只知道說
That temperature is higher than the temperature of liquid nitrogen
那個溫度是高過液態氮的溫度
That was incredible, a very big breakthrough
那是不得了,非常大的一個突破
Because in the laboratory, laying eggs is like drinking boiled water
因為在實驗室裡面,一胎蛋就像我們平常喝開水一樣
That is to say, it is actually possible to obtain
就是說其實可以拿得到的
Meaning you cool it below the temperature of a fetal egg
意思就是說你在一胎蛋的溫度把它冷卻之下
superconductivity can be achieved, and a lot of research can be done
就可以達到超導,可以做很多的研究
Can save a lot of energy
可以省下很多的能源
So Wu Maohui Academy is his contribution
所以吳茂輝院是他的貢獻
his understanding of the material
他對材料方面的理解
This experience provides a very important support for our team
這個方面的經驗提供我們這個團隊非常重要的一個資助
In addition to this, Professor Zhou Fangzheng of National Taiwan University Lingtai Center is a Crystal Grower
除了這個之外台大靈太中心周方正教授他是一個掌金Crystal Grower
Many thermoelectric materials rely on gold
很多的熱電材料就是要靠掌金來的
Professor Zhang Zhiwei is very experienced in the analysis of a structure of Nimi and his heat conduction telecommunications
張智威教授他對耐米的一個結構他的熱傳導電信的分析非常有經驗
In the end, Xie Wenbin from the Institute of Earth Sciences started to be a thermal teacher and assistant researcher. He should have given birth recently, right?
最後地球所的謝文斌開始的熱師從助研究員他最近應該生了吧
He's been doing really well lately and he's really good at measuring heat conduction.
最近做得很好他在對熱傳導的測量各方面非常的專精
We formed such a team, of course except for this account
我們組了這樣的一個團隊當然除了這個帳面
In fact, there are many involved behind the scenes
事實上背後旁邊還有很多參與的
For example, Professor Lin Lixiong present here
譬如說在座的林立雄教授
Director of the Front Desk Da Ning Tai Center
前台大寧太中心的主任
also my other half
也是我的另一半
He's actually been involved in this project all along.
他事實上一直在參與這個計畫裡面
Just saying the name doesn't stand here
只是說名字沒有立在這裡
I often say
我常常會講說
I myself was born to learn electrical engineering
我自己是學電機出生
So it is clearer about electricity
所以對電性比較清楚
familiar with light
對光也比較熟
But when it comes to materials
但是對材料的時候
When you come across the structure of this material
當你碰到這個材料的結構
you put it up
你把它擺起來
you turn it
你把它轉
what is its symmetry
它的對稱性是怎麼樣
get this done
這一搞下來
I usually just get dizzy
我常常就是搞到昏頭戰相
But luckily when I get sleepy
但是還好我碰到困了的時候
I give it to my wife
我交給我太太
She can help me out soon
她很快就可以幫我解出來
say how it should be
說應該是怎麼樣
So although her name is not posted here
所以她的名字雖然沒有立在這裡
I especially acknowledge her
我特別Acknowledge她一下
Okay, let's go back to what thermoelectricity is. Simply put, you have a heat, and then, in the process of heat dissipation, it will generate electricity at the same time.
好,那我們回到說這個什麼叫熱電,簡單的講就是你有一個熱,然後呢,它這個散熱的過程,它同時會產生電出來。
As for this thing, about two hundred years ago, this Sebeck discovered such a phenomenon.
那這個東西呢,在大概將近兩百年前,這個Sebeck,他發現了這樣的一個現象。
In fact, if you look at his original picture, he found that when he put a metal material through one end and heated it, the heat will flow to the other end.
事實上,你如果來看他當初這個圖,他發現的時候,他是把一個金屬材料,然後通一端加熱,然後熱會流到另一端來。
At the same time, he found out that he put one, which is similar to a pointer, the pointer is here, and found that the pointer can move, and then felt very, very...
同時呢,他發現說他放了一個,類似指針針,指針在這裡,發現說這個指針會動,然後覺得很,很...
Very surprised
很意外
Then he thought
然後他就認為說
This magnetic field is caused by heat
因為熱的關係導致這個磁場
creates a magnetic field
會產生一個磁場
Not long after that it was confirmed that
那不久以後就證實說
In fact, his original idea was wrong.
其實他的本來的想法是錯的
It's because after the heat flow
是因為熱流過來以後
He will also drive a current
他同時會帶動一個電流
We know this current
那這個電流我們知道
Electricity and magnetism are closely related
電跟磁是息息相關的
because of current
因為有電流
So the generated magnetic field deflects the pointer
所以產生的磁場把這個指針偏動了
so what
那所以呢
We call this thing C-Back Effect
這個東西我們叫做C-Back Effect
discovered 200 years ago
在200年前發現
Then such an Effect
那這樣的一個Effect
In fact if you are a material
事實上如果你是一根材料
it can also
它也可以
But why do we often draw two
但為什麼我們常常會畫兩根
We'll tell you later
我們等一下會跟大家介紹說
Why do they usually come in pairs?
為什麼一般都要成雙成對
It will be more efficient
它的效率會比較高
then say another
那再說個
After the discovery of the thermoelectric effect
這個發現的這個熱電效應之後啊
it's been ten years
它在過了十幾年
Another French scientist named Patel
法國的另外一個科學家叫Patel
he found out
他發現說
If I am in certain materials
我如果在某一些材料啊
After I turned it on
我把它通了電以後
he found out
他發現說
one end can get very hot
有一端可以變很熱
even
甚至於呢
one end can get very cold
有一端可以變得很冷
it's upside down
這是倒過來了
that is
就是說
Because of the cold temperature difference
這邊因為有冷溫度差
T degree difference so generate electricity
T度差別所以產生電
what about here
那這邊呢
he means
他是說
If I use current
我如果用電流
Make a voltage to make it generate a current
弄了一個電壓讓它產生電流
One end of the material found to be hot
發現材料的一端會熱
the other end will get cold
另外一端會變冷
At first
當初啊
these discoveries
這個這些發現
caused a lot
引起很多的
everyone's attention
大家的注意
Research
研究
So what about this thing?
所以呢這個東西呢
In our general textbooks, there are
在我們一般的教科書裡面都有
Wait until later this is called Tomson
一直等到後來這個叫做Tomson
This William Thompson he just came to know about it
這個William Thompson他才了解出來講說
In fact, these two things are two sides of the same coin.
其實這兩件事是一體兩面
It's the same thing upside down
就是倒過來是同一回事
I have T degrees of temperature and I can generate electricity
我有溫度的T度我可以產生電
Upside down I push it back with electricity
倒過來我用電把它推回去
Electricity pushes it back and I can generate heat
電把它推回去我可以產生熱
or a difference in temperature
或者是產生溫度的差異
is the same thing
是同一件事情
It even takes the two coefficients
它甚至於把這兩個系數
It is CBF and PADF
就是CBF and PADF
Association between two coefficients
兩個系數之間的關聯
express it mathematically
用數學把它表示出來
that is a very important contribution
那是相當的重要的一個貢獻
Then this William Thompson
那這個William Thompson
He was later dubbed the British
他後來被英國把它封為
Lore Kevin
Lore Kevin
I'm curious about this
這個我就很好奇了
Strange, his name is Thompson
奇怪 他的名字明明叫Thompson
Then why is it called Kevin
那為什麼叫Kevin
Everyone knows Lore
Lore大家就知道
In England they have this class of different nobility
在英國他們有這個不同貴族的階級
some what sir
有一些什麼爵士
some monkey prince or something
有些什麼猴爵之類的
Then he was named Lore Kevin
那他被封為Lore Kevin
should have made a great contribution
應該是有很大的貢獻
Then why is it called Kevin
那為什麼叫Kevin
If I were Lore Thompson
要是我應該是Lore Thompson
Why Lore Kevin
為什麼是Lore Kevin
In fact
事實上呢
I think his contribution
我覺得他的這個貢獻
Another contribution is even greater
另外一個貢獻是更偉大的
He pushed it down and said
他啦 他推倒出來說
have a temperature
有一個溫度
called the absolute temperature absolute zero
叫做絕對溫度絕對零度
Wow, this is actually today
哇這個其實今天要是
It is not easy for ordinary guests to think about this
讓一般的客人家來想都不容易想到這個
the idea we know
這個想法我們知道說
All objects have a certain temperature
這個所有的物體它都有一定的溫度
Touch our heads, do you have a fever today?
摸摸我們的頭今天有沒有發燒對不對
Or this cold snap is coming, it's cold outside
或者說這個寒流來了這個外面很冷
Slowly humans figured out and said
慢慢的人類想出來說
With the concept of temperature, there can be heat
有溫度這個概念有能有熱
Right? Well, then what?
對不對好那後來呢
There is a scientist who should be from Denmark or Sweden
有一位應該是丹麥或者是瑞典的科學家
Called Selces
叫做Selces
He put the water
他就把水的
The freezing temperature is the same as the boiling temperature of water
結冰那個溫度跟水這個沸騰那個溫度
Eight hundred and one hundred grid
八分一百格
hundredths
一百等分
that is our facility today
那就是今天我們的設施
Facility temperature
設施溫度
I remember going to
我記得那時候去
when denmark
丹麥的時候
there is one
有一個
it was a museum
那時候是一個博物館
still in front of a train station
還是一個火車站的前面
Huanong has a very large thermometer
華農有一個非常大的溫度計
Then there is DoC not DoF
然後是DoC 不是DoF
that's why
那因為呢
he just wants
他就是要
Xiu said you have a look
秀說你看看
This Sales is someone from their country
這個Sales is 就是他們國家的人
That
那
Originally set the temperature
當初把溫度
Use a few degrees C facility a few degrees
用幾度C 設施幾度
Then turn this temperature into 100 divisions
然後把這個溫度化成100格
really full
確實是滿實在的
Everyone is using it everyday
大家現在日常都在用
but
但是呢
from that facility
從那個設施
to what we call absolute temperature
到我們叫絕對溫度
this is not easy
這個是很不容易的
But it's not easy
但是不容易啊
that is
就是說
If we take a
我們如果把一個
material or even biological activity
材料也好或者甚至生物的活性
I don't know that no one knew or understood him back then
我不曉得他當初沒有人知道沒有了解
When he got this Tomson
當初這個Tomson他得到的時候
That is to say, you put a certain
就是說你把某一個
Look at the vibration of atoms or what kind of
看是原子的振動或者是什麼樣呢
He transformed this activity into a coordinate with temperature
他把這個活性隨著溫度化了一個坐標
Then this activity becomes smaller and smaller
然後這個活性越來越小
If you push to a certain activity when it is as small as 0
你如果推到某一個活性小到0的時候
He found out that the temperature was -273.16 degrees
他發現說那個溫度是-273.16度
From that time onwards
從那個時候推展出來說
There is a temperature called absolute zero
有一個溫度叫絕對零度
at that temperature
在那個溫度的時候
all things will stand still
所有的東西都會靜止
All creatures are lifeless
所有的生物也沒有生命啦
All objects stop when they are at absolute latitude
所有的物體全部是絕對凌度的時候都停止啦
OK
OK
so from this
那從這樣子呢
it got this calvin
它得到了這個Calvin
is the absolute temperature
就是絕對溫度
That's why it was knighted
那也因為這樣子它被封了這個爵士
Law, didn't I say Law is called Jazz?
Law 我不是講Law是叫爵士嗎
It's a knighthood, okay?
封的爵位啦 好不好
this is really important
這個確實是很重要
Although it is not directly related to today's hot spots
雖然說跟今天的熱點沒有直接的關係啦
That absolute temperature
那個絕對溫度啊
You seem to say fate
你像說緣分所
What about Fate, we have four groups
緣分所呢 我們有一四個組
One of them is called AMO
其中有一個組呢 叫做AMO
Atomic Molecular and Optics
Atomic Molecular and Optics
What about this group?
這一組的人呢
have a very special plan
有一個很特殊的計畫
that is
就是說
This atom or molecule, has been cooling energy
這個原子或分子的,一直冷卻能能能
How cold can it be?
能到多冷呢?
You said absolute temperature, absolute zero
你說絕對溫度,絕對零度
In fact, no one has ever reached absolute zero.
其實到現在沒有任何人到達過絕對零度
it's hard
就很難
That's all right, then use various methods to cool it under liquid nitrogen
那沒有關係,那就用各種方法把它冷到液態氮底下
liquid liquid nitrogen, and even colder, liquid hydrogen
液體液態氮,再來更冷,液態氫
not enough, colder, liquid helium
再不夠,再更冷,液態氦
Liquid helium depends on which kind of helium
液態氦就看哪一種氦
It's two or three degrees below absolute temperature
它就到絕對溫度的兩三度了
ok , not cold enough
好,還不夠冷
There is a Nobel laureate named Zhu Liwen
那有一位諾貝爾獎得主叫朱利文
He just uses a laser
他就是用雷射
Take this atomic molecule and make it move smaller and smaller
把這個原子分子把它弄到讓它動得越越小
then reached a few
那就到達了幾個
Our name is Milly Kevin
我們叫Milly Kevin
minus 3 degrees absolute temperature
負3度絕對溫度
wow smaller
哇 更小了
But actually that is not enough
但是呢 其實那個都還不夠能
early in science
在科學上很早就有人
Derivation There is a thing called Bose Einstein
推導 有一個東西叫做Bose Einstein
Condensation Einstein
Condensation Einstein
everyone knows
大家都很清楚
Another one is from India
另外有一位就是印度的
Scientists call Bose VOSE
科學家叫Bose VOSE
They theoretically deduce that
他們理論上推導說
you take this substance
你把這個物質
to a certain extent
一直能到某一個程度的時候
it becomes another state
它會變成另外一種狀態
we just know
我們就知道說
A substance is either a gas or a liquid
物質不然就是氣態 不然就是液態
otherwise solid state
不然就是固態
but he said no
但是他說不是
At that point it was called Bose Einstein
到那個程度的時候它叫Bose Einstein
The Condensation is another completely
的Condensation 是另外一種完全
status no one has seen
沒有人看過的狀態
Theoretical derivation
理論上推導
Seventy or eighty years later
這個七八十年以後
It was proved experimentally that
這個實驗上被證明說
really called BEC
真的有叫BEC
This Bose Einstein Matter Exists
Bose Einstein的這個物質存在
that's a hot topic
那就是一個很熱門的一個話題
so what
所以呢
This BEC
這個BEC啊
just close to
就是一直接近到
For example, rich six
十的譬如說富六
called Microkevin
叫做Microkevin
Now the laboratory can do
現在的實驗室可以做到
Nano-Calvin is even lower
Nano-Calvin甚至更低
It's very, very close to absolute zero.
就是非常非常的接近絕對零度
so what
所以呢
This conception of light from temperature
光從溫度的這個構想
to absolute temperature
到了絕對溫度
That's what we just talked about
那到了我們剛剛講的
you can approach
你可以逼近
How close to absolute zero
多麼的逼近絕對零度
What about this matter?
那這一件事情呢
actually
其實
is in what we call
是在我們叫做
Cold science, it is very cold
冷科學了,就是非常冷
How to do this very very cold low temperature
怎麼樣去做到這個非常非常冷的低的溫度
ok then we come back
好,那我們回來
So, this Tomson has made great contributions
所以呢,這個Tomson他有很大的貢獻
As for thermoelectricity, he combined two phenomena
那在熱電方面呢,他把兩個現象
string it up
把它串起來
We call this thermoelectric material two sides of one body
我們叫這個熱電材料的一體兩面
In fact, we will introduce two phenomena in a moment.
其實兩種現象等一下我們會介紹
it all works
它都有用
Well, I didn't introduce this to you
好,另外這個我沒有跟大家介紹
A man named Gustav Magnus
一個叫做Gustav Magnus
It is to combine materials, different materials
它呢,是把材料,不同的材料
do some experiments like
去做類似的一些實驗
In the end, it turns out that what we call
最後呢,它發現就是我們所謂的
thermocouple
熱偶, thermocouple
We are often in the laboratory, in some laboratories that do physics
我們常常在實驗室,在有些做物理的實驗室
you want a high temperature
你要的溫度要很高
this one thousand degrees
這個一千度的
Some are four Baidu
有的就是四百度的
then you have some zero degrees
那你有一些是零度的
200 degrees, how to measure these temperatures
200度的,這些溫度要怎麼測量
The most common is to use two different metals
最常用的就是用兩個不同的金屬
then chain it together
然後把它連在一起
it will get a potential difference
它就會得到一個電位差
That potential difference is related to its temperature
那個電位差跟它的溫度有關
So, that thing
所以呢,那個東西
This phenomenon is actually related to the material
這個現象其實是跟材料
its nature is related
它的性質是相關的
good
好
come again, this one
再來呢,這一位
called Yof
叫做Yof
what about yofy , he ' s a soviet
Yofy呢,他是一個蘇聯人
What about him
他呢
around 1900
在大概1900年左右
he just said
他就提出來說
use a pair
要用一對的
First, he uses semiconductor
第一方面他用半導體
Two sides use a pair, we call P type and N type
二方面用一對,我們叫P型跟N型
Inside, on the semiconductor surface, there are some positive charges on it.
這裏面啦,半導體面啦,它有一些是代正的這個電荷
There is a kind of charge that replaces more negative charges
那有一種是代比較多負電的電荷
He said, put two times and two times in pairs
他說,把兩個乘雙乘對這樣做起來啦
it can get the highest efficiency
它可以得到最高的效率
This is also very important, so you see
這個也是非常重要,所以你看
the soviet stamp
這個蘇聯的郵票
This is 1980, and that was the Soviet Union
這是1980,那還是蘇聯
Soviet Union stamps, there it is
蘇聯的郵票,就有它
That's not the only way, if everyone goes
那不只這樣子,如果大家去
That St. Petersburg, let me see, raise your hand if you have been to Russia
那個聖彼得堡,我看看,去過俄羅斯的舉手
Many people should have been there, Russia
應該很多人去過吧,俄羅斯
doesn't he? no, don't be so polite
他沒有嗎?不會吧,別那麼客氣
Have you ever been to St. Petersburg? Raise your hand
聖彼得堡去過沒有?舉手一下
How many have been
有幾位去過
you went to st petersburg again
你又有去聖彼得堡
Of course you went to see that so-and-so, that so-and-so East Palace in Kaiserling, right?
當然你又去看那個什麼,凱撒林的那個什麼東宮,是不是
wow that's beautiful isn't it
哇,那很漂亮,對不對
What about St. Petersburg?
那聖彼得堡呢
The most important scientific research unit
最重要的科學研究單位
It's called YORF Institute
叫做YORF Institute
is to commemorate it with its name
就是用它的名字來紀念它
then it's on the thermoelectric
那它在熱電上面
it says on the first side it says
它說 第一方面它說
This semiconductor is better than this metal material
這個半導體比這個金屬材料
or other materials or insulating materials
或者是其他材料或者絕緣材料
Suitable
適合
this is very important
這是蠻重要的
second it says
第二個它又說
The material is the best
這個材料裡面最好
have a pair
要有一對
One is P-type material
一個是P型的材質
The other one is N-type material
另外一個是N型的材質
One is a positively charged material
一個是正電的材質
One is a negatively charged material
一個是負電的材質
make it paired later
讓它成對起來以後
everyone can watch
大家可以看
its electricity
它的電
It can run like this
它電可以這樣走這樣來
So electricity is connected in series
所以電是串聯的
two things in series
兩個東西串聯
strung together these two are strung together
串起來 這兩個是串起來的
but it's hot
但是熱呢
hot here is hot
熱這邊是熱
here is can
這邊是能
heat is electricity
熱是電
This is very strange, our...
這個就很奇特了,我們這場...
It is not easy for you to think that there is a structure that can make heat and electricity
你不容易想到說有一個結構可以讓熱跟電
let one be in series, one patient
讓它一個是串聯,一個病人
Then if it is changed in this way, its efficiency can reach the highest
那如果這樣變起來以後,它的效率可以達到最高
So why do we often have a lot of materials?
所以為什麼我們常常很多材料呢
Thermoelectric materials wait for everyone to see
熱電材料等一下大家來看
It's all one-on-one
都是一對一對的
This thing is at the back
這個東西呢,就到了後面
Let me take a look, okay, let me tell you first
我看一下,好,先跟大家講就是
Most of the current thermoelectric materials look like this
目前大部分的熱電材料都長成這個樣子
It looks like this one by one
看起來就是一根一根的這樣一個
Let's call Array, get it up
我們叫Array,把它弄起來
Well, among them, they are all in pairs, pairs, pairs, pairs
那其中呢,都是成雙成對成雙成對
can achieve the highest efficiency
可以達到最高的效率
So here I have brought some materials
所以我這邊呢,有帶了幾個材料
It's an oil price company called Malo
是油價公司叫Malo
Take a look and let you pass it on
你看一下,讓你傳下去知道
What does this material look like?
這個材料到底長的什麼樣子
OK
好不好
Just look at it and get a feeling
大家看一下才有一個感覺
What about this material?
那這個材料呢
Around the 1940s and 1950s
在大概1940、50年代
Very
非常地
Then it became very popular
後來就非常的熱門
whether it is the soviet union
不管是蘇聯
Regardless of the United States, etc. are actively researching
不管美國等等都積極地研究
For example, the earliest product
譬如說這個最早的一個產品
Just a thermoelectric with an oil lamp
就是一個熱電用一個油燈
light up
點起來
Then this heat goes to generate electricity
然後這個熱去發電
This electricity to power a radio
這個電來推動一個收音機
Your radio uses its power
你收音機就用它的電
then i don't have a radio today
那我今天沒有收音機
I brought this thing for everyone to see
我就帶了這個東西給大家看
this is also a
這個也是一個
put a candle underneath
底下放一個蠟燭
In the future, one side of the thermoelectric material will be heated.
以後呢就把這個熱電材料的一邊加熱了
after heating
加熱了以後呢
this
這個
You can see the LED lights
LED的燈大家可以看得到
that will be bright
那就是會亮
That
那
Of course everyone will feel very bored, right?
大家當然會覺得很大悶對不對
Then you already have candles and you need to light them again
那你已經有蠟燭了你要再點
What do you do with that LED?
點那個LED那幹什麼
right
對不對
then you are not this
那你不是這個
what are we going to do
我們做什麼
Your word is Diago Gipson
你的話叫Diago Gipson
Take the monkey to the mountain
把猴子做到山裡面去
what to do
幹什麼
but
但是呢
if one day
如果有一天
You're going to climb a mountain and you're suddenly stuck in the mountain
你在你去爬山去登山然後突然間困在山裡面
Then your mobile phone has been used
然後呢你的手機已經用
This is out of power
這個沒電了
Then you asked to save him and found that
那你要求救他發現說
this
這個
No electricity
沒有電
if there is this
如果有這個的話
he can save your life
他就可以救你一命
Of course it's more than that. It's just a
那當然不只這樣了這只是一個
An example would be to say
一個示範就是說
your simple one
你簡單的一個
oil lamp
油燈
How is it possible to generate electricity
有怎么可能来产生电
Then wait a minute, this is over, everyone can take a look
那等一下这个结束了,大家可以看一下
So, at that time
所以呢,在那个时代
either the soviet union
无论是那个苏联
Many people in the United States are concerned about this thermoelectric material
美国,大家很多人就对这个热电材料
have high dreams
有很高的梦想
What dream? That is to say, if the material efficiency is high
什么梦想呢?就是说,这个材料效率如果做高的话
then i don't need that internal combustion engine, i don't need that engine
那我不需要那个内燃机,我不需要那个引擎
That engine though we have it in every car, right?
那个引擎虽然我们在每辆车上都有,对不对
That car is noisy, you know that engine
那个车子很吵啊,你知道那个引擎
It explodes every time, go push this spin of yours
它每一次都爆炸,去推动你的这个旋转
If this efficiency is high enough
那如果是这个效率够高的话
then you burn it up and heat it up
那你就把它燃烧,热出来
It turns into electricity, no noise, very stable
就轉成電了,不會有噪音,很穩定
So at that time, many countries were developing this thermal power
所以那個時候很多國家都在發展這個熱電
I want to say that one day it will really become a mainstream
想說哪一天它真的是變成一個主流
Then such an effort lasted until about the 1970s
那這樣的一個努力一直到了大概1970年代
In the end, I found out that it doesn't seem to be true.
最後發現說好像真的不行
Let's take a look at this in 1960 when
我們來看看這個在1960年的時候
The first paper 1954
第一篇paper 1954
This one is called Gullsmith
這個叫做Gullsmith
He used a material called Bismuth Terrarium
他用了一個材料叫Bismuth Terrarium
Is Geochem B
地化B是不是
This material is now turned into a commercial thermoelectric material
這個材料現在變成商用的熱電材料裡面
is the most widely used
是最廣泛用的
This Gullsmith is number one
這個Gullsmith他是第一
One cools it with thermoelectric method to cool it
一個把冷卻 用熱電的方法把它冷卻
Cool the material down to sub-zero
把材料的冷卻到零度以下
zero degrees is of course a big milestone
零度當然是一個很重要的里程碑
So this establishes a milestone
所以這個就建立了一個里程碑
Of course Ghost Miss was originally called Chicago
當然Ghost Miss 原來叫Chicago
Has many contributions to thermoelectricity including writing this book
在熱電方面有很多貢獻包括寫的這本書
It doesn't just write a book, it just lists a
它不只寫一本書 只是列了一個
Recently, after getting older, it recently moved to Australia
最近年紀大了以後 它最近轉到澳洲去了
It's a very well-known figure in the thermoelectric community
它在熱電界是一個非常知名的人物
I've just covered most of the material
我剛剛已經講了 大部分的材料
Now pass it down for everyone to see, it looks like this
現在傳下去給大家看的 它都長的這個樣子
Then it depends on your thickness and height
那就看 你這個厚度 高度要多少
If you want to generate electricity, the hot and cold
你如果要發電的話 這個熱跟冷
There must be a temperature difference
要有一個溫度的差
The bigger the temperature difference, the better
溫度的差越大越好
so what
所以呢
If you are too thin
那你太薄的話
You can't get it up if you have a temperature difference
你的溫度差就弄不起來
so generally
所以一般
it also has a certain distance
它也要有一定的距離
so it can't be made too thin
所以它沒有辦法做得太薄
but if you want to cool down
但你如果是要冷卻的話
it will be easier
會容易一點
cool down
冷卻
this can be done
這個可以做的
even do it with thin film
甚至用薄膜來做
Then everyone can see
到時候大家可以看
Then what
然後呢
There is another important
歷史上還有一個重要的
there are two people
有兩個人
This is Cody and Abel
這是Cody and Abel
where are they
他們呢
in the 1960s
在1960年代的時候
he was the first to propose
他第一個提出
用Silicon Germanium
用Silicon Germanium
this fold
這個摺
Folding system or refinement
摺化系或細化摺
inside the table table
在桌子表裡面
It is folded tin sign from carbon series
它是從碳系摺錫簽
If you were tabled when you were a child
如果小時候被桌子表的話
it folds the tie
它把系跟摺
get it together
弄在一起
become a
變成一個
this alloy
這個合金
That
那
they figured it out
他們就推算了
This material can be made into a good thermoelectric material
這個材料可以做成熱電很好的材料
Sure enough, the details about Silicon Jumenium
果然後面有關Silicon Jumenium 細化質
The first one it can go from room temperature of 300 to 1100 degrees K
第一個它可以從300的室溫到1100度K
It is stable at very high temperatures
非常高的溫度它都很穩定
The second more important thing is that it has a radioactive element
第二個更重要的就是它有一個放射性元素
called Putonium
叫做Putonium
This Putonium it's dangerous
這個Putonium它很危險
After our nuclear power plant produces nuclear power
我們的核能電廠右產生了核電以後
One of its products is this thing
它的產物之一就是這個東西
That's because of the radioactive elements in this thing
那就是因為這個東西它的放射性元素
Radiation is still strong
放射還是很強
So we don't know what to do with the nuclear waste
所以我們對這些核廢料不曉得怎麼處理
And look at this half-life of 24,000 years
而且你看這個半衰期24000年
After it was produced, you said it was not good and you left it
產生以後你說它不好你把它放著
Just leave it for a long time
放久了就好
Is it okay? It will be reduced to half after 24,000 years
就好了嗎?要放兩萬四千年以後才減到一半
So why does everyone have such a headache about nuclear waste?
所以為什麼大家對核廢料那麼都很頭痛
But, it doesn't mean that this material is useless
但是呢,這個材料不是說就沒有用途啊
it this
它這個
Because it will always release the medium fat and alpha
因為它會一直放出中脂跟阿法的這個
this particle
這個particle
It will generate a lot of heat when it hits this metal
它打到這個金屬以後它會產生很大的熱
Then it puts out the heat of this radioactive element
然後它就把這個放射性元素放出來的熱
become hot
變成熱
To provide silicon germanium to do thermoelectricity to generate electricity
來提供silicon germanium去做熱電來發電
Then what
然後呢
This power supply made in this way
用這樣子做出來的這個電源
Provided a lot of Apollo this pioneer
提供了很多阿波羅這個先鋒號
The Pioneer seems to have exploded during Longe
先鋒號好像有一次Longe的時候爆炸掉了
Then vacuum, Voyager, Galaxia, Jellilie, etc.
然後呢vacuum, Voyager, Galaxia, Jellilie等等
Many, many spaceships all use
很多很多的太空船全部用
This method means that everyone can see
這個方法,就是說大家來看
It's something, it's a Voyager
它的東西啊,這是一個Voyager
its this spaceship
它的這個太空船
In addition to all kinds of
那它除了各式各樣的
Cameras, other than communication equipment
照相機啦,通信設備之外
where its power
其中它的電源
From this one, it's called RTG
來自這一個,它叫做RTG
RadioIsotope, just that Plutonium
RadioAstope,就是剛剛那個Putonium
It's called the Confidence Element, and then what?
它叫做自信元素,然後呢
Somoelectric is Silicon Dominium
Somoelectric,就是Silicon Dominium
and then generate electricity
然後把它產生電
Then its detailed structure looks like this
那它的細部結構就像這樣子
I don't think I need to explain it to you carefully.
我想就不用跟你很仔細的解釋
That is to say, it basically takes Putonium
就是說它基本上呢,把Putonium
Put this on, it's hot, it's hot
這個放,很熱很熱
This element is placed here, and after hitting the surface
這個元素放在這裡,然後打到這個表面以後呢
it takes heat, puts it here, and pours
它把熱,放在這裡,然後倒
Then through thermoelectric materials, and finally
然後經過熱電材料,然後最後呢
Pass the electricity, this one out
把電,這個傳出來
Of course, many people will wonder
當然很多人會很納悶說
Our normal spacecraft don't need this
我們一般的太空船不需要用這個
You can use solar panels, right?
你用太陽能板就好了 對不對
while outer space is running
外太空在跑的時候
The sun is stronger than the surface of the earth
陽光比地球表面還要強
then why do you need this
那為什麼需要這個
In fact, ordinary spaceships
事實上一般的太空船
In fact, it would be better to use solar panels
其實它用太陽能板就好了
But there are many special uses
但是有很多特殊的用途
Come and see everyone
來跟大家看一下
For example, this is the Voyager sailing plus
譬如說這個是Voyager航海加號
it rises from the earth
它從地球上面
around 1776
在1776年左右
There are two Voyager 1 and Voyager 2
有兩個Voyager 1跟Voyager 2
two nautical pluses
兩個航海加號
slippery as it wanders
它浪跡的一樣用滑溜
Rocket ascends to outer space
火箭升到外太空
and start orbiting the earth
然後開始繞著地球
centripetal force
離心力跟向心力
just kept going around there
就一直在那邊繞
around to a certain extent
繞到某一個程度的時候
it gives a little motivation
它給了一點點動力
then from the earth
然後就從地球
pull this is a
拉到這個是一個
Jupiter
Jupiter
to the next planet
到下一個行星
and go around to it over there
然後在那邊繞到它
All the pictures to be probed have been taken
要探測的所有的照片都拍好了
then give it a little more motivation
然後再給一點點動力
It ran to the next one to Saturn
它又跑到下一個到Saturn
even what
甚至是什麼
Uranus or Minwang
天王星還是敏王星
ancestor star
祖星
then to Uranus
然後到Uranus
Jupiter goes down one by one
木星一個一個下去
It uses a very clever
它用這樣的非常聰明的
a physical method
一個物理的方法
use very little energy
用很少的能量
just use its centrifugal force
就用它那個離心力
it goes from one to one to one
它從一個到一個到一個
and put the whole sun
然後把整個太陽
Visit all these stars
在這幾個星星全部探訪
Even I remember when there were several stars with their moons
甚至我記得當初有好幾個星星有它的月亮
didn't know before
以前是不知道的
Because this Voyager went to shoot very clearly
因為這個 Voyager去了拍得很清楚
such a contribution
這樣的一個貢獻
Everyone should know that you are on Earth
大家要知道你在地球
you might be on mars
你可能在火星上面
strong sunlight
陽光很強
No problem with solar version
跟太陽能版沒有問題
but
但是呢
you are farther away
你到了遠一點
to Saturn
到了土星
to Jupiter
到了木星去
too far from the sun
離太陽太遠
not enough sunlight
陽光根本不夠
Provide the solar energy you want
提供你你要的太陽能
so what
所以呢
why it needs to be used
它為什麼需要用
radioactive elements
放射性的元素
Then come to provide power
然後來提供電力
that's how it came
就是這樣來的
then everyone can watch
那大家可以看
because it is radioactive
因為它有放射性
in the process of claiming
在主張的過程
all
所有的
to be in this
要在這個
All the space suits in this Clean Room have to be worn
這個Clean Room裡面全部太空裝要穿起來
Do you know why? Why is it needed?
大家知道為什麼嗎?為什麼需要?
Just put it back on
裝回去就好了
There is no need for the auxiliary line, there is no way to block this
輔助線不用啊,這個也沒有辦法擋下
Auxiliary line, you have to wear Qianyi
輔助線你要穿千衣
why is this? you need to know
這個是為什麼呢?你要知道
You go take an X-ray
你去照X光啊
Tell you how many times I take a photo
跟你講說我照一次是多少個
how many doses is it right
多少劑量對不對?豪西佛什麼的
Then you said, it’s best not to take more than a few times a year
那你說啊這個一年最好不要照超過幾次
Too many security photos are not good
比較安全照太多的不好
everybody knows
大家都知道
But today if you say
但是今天如果說
we have a composite
我們有一個合費料
or radial rebar
或者是輻射鋼筋
if one day
如果有一天啊
you accidentally sucked into your body
你不小心吸到你的身體裡面
Then the radioactive substance stays in your body
然後那個放射性的物質就留在你體內的話
It's like an X-ray inside a body
它就像一個體內的一個X光
I've been taking photos with you
一直在跟你照
then you are very very dangerous
那你就非常非常危險
Because if you suck it in, you can't get it out
因為你如果吸進去排不出來
and stay inside you
然後就停留在你體內
it goes on and on
它就持續不斷之
within its half-period
只要在它的半塞期之內
it just keeps emitting this radiation
它就一直發射這個輻射
so it's very dangerous
所以是很危險很危險的
so what
所以呢
Absolutely no radiation pollution
絕對不能有輻射污染
Or it's the same when you go to a nuclear power plant
或者說你到核電廠也是一樣
You can't let radioactive material get into your body
你不能讓放射性的物質跑到你的體內
good
好
this is a
這個呢是一個
this nautical plus spaceship
這個航海加號的太空船
this person is special
這個人很特別
His name is Ed Stone
他的名字叫Ed Stone
He was the host of the project
是當初這個計畫的主持人
NASA
NASA
When Launch Voyager
當初Launch Voyager
his host
他的主持人
that was very successful
那非常的成功
Everyone can think of AZ
大家可以想阿茲
I just told you
剛剛已經跟大家講了
Skip from planet to planet Skip from planet to planet
從一個星球跳過一個星球跳過一個星球
Walk all the stars of the sun
把整個太陽的星星全部都走一遍
Many people will ask him
那很多人會問他說
What about going to the last one?
那走到最後一個怎麼辦
Does anyone know
有沒有人知道
What is the one that went the furthest after the detection?
這個探測完了走到最遠的那個是什麼
star?
明王星嗎
after that
那之後呢
No
沒有啊
What are the hundreds of millions of planets in the universe afraid of?
宇宙上億個那麼多星球怕什麼
Just go to the next planet after this
這個走完就到下一個星球去就好了
Does anyone know
有沒有人知道
where is he going
他要去哪裡
Next target
下一個目標
Does anyone know
有沒有人知道
Guess
猜得到
There are so many planets in the universe
宇宙的星球非常非常的多
Now, of course, the light pollution of the special style is relatively tight.
現在當然特別式的光害比較緊
If you go for diplomacy, take a look
交外去的話一看
Wow, that star is too many to count
哇 那個星星非常的數不盡
I went back to my home in Nantou a while ago
有前一陣子回我南投的家
come with some relatives
跟一些親戚來
Wow, they looked at it and said wow, why is this
哇 他們看說哇 這個為什麼
There are so many stars in Nantou
南投這個星星那麼的多
and then the terrible
然後更那個可怕的
have a child like this
有一個這個小子女吧
She clicked on this phone or that app
她把這個手機那個app一點下去
She calls out every star
每一顆星星她都叫出來
OK now just say
OK 現在就是說
Your GPS knows where your location is
你的GPS知道你的地點在哪裡
The second you know when your date is
第二個你知道你的日期是什麼時候
Every star on her phone
她那個手機上面的每一顆星星
Correspond to the stars in your sky one by one
跟你天空的星星一一對應
We used to get half a day there
我們以前常常會在那邊搞到半天
Oh, which one is the Big Dipper?
哦 這個到底哪一個是北斗星
oh which one is the star
哦 哪一個是什麼星
right now no more
對 現在都不用了
Take it out and pair it up
一拿出來一對著
Oh this is her this is her
哦 這個就是她 這個就是她
This kid seems to be very happy now
這個現在的小孩子好像很幸福了
won't probably lose some of the fun too
不會可能也失去了一些樂趣
what to say
嗯 いう的
This nautical plus to the last star star
這個航海加號到了最後一個明王星
It's actually been, maybe three or four years ago
事實上已經過了,大概三四年前
He ran from the earth for forty years
他從地球跑了四十年
Then of course you can design him and see how long he goes around
那你當然可以設計他,看他繞多久
But it takes years to go between each star
但每一顆星中間要走幾年的時間
OK, run like this
OK,這樣跑
ok , to the back
好啦,到後面
Of course he can wait and say, then I'll go out
他當然可以等說,那我再出去
It may take many years to wait, and it is possible to go to the next planet
可能要等多少年以後,有可能會到下一個星球
But maybe two or three hundred years later
但是可能是兩三百年以後
Do you have the impression that we are talking about the distance between the stars
大家有沒有印象,我們在講星星的距離
Of course, there are tens of thousands of light years, or even hundreds of millions of light years.
當然都是幾萬光年,甚至是幾億光年都有
That's just running away, not man would have already run away
那是光跑的,不是人造會已經跑了
Man-made numbers that can run may be 1/1000th of light
人造會跑的數字都可能沒有光的1千分之一
that means
那意思就是說
There are many galaxies, but space is still very lonely
星系很多,但是太空還是很孤獨的
You're going from one solar system to the next
你要從一個太陽系走到下一個星系
And it might be a long, long time
而可能就是很久很久以後了
So, here I will make a picture
所以呢,這邊我就弄一個圖
This is Eston, when he joined NASA very young
這個是Eston,他加入NASA很年輕的時候
This is him two years ago, our thermoelectric society
這個是他兩年前,我們一個熱電學會
In Pasadena, at the Celtic
在Pasadena,在Celtic那邊舉辦
Eston came to tell us the story of Voyager
Eston來跟我們演講Voyager的故事
what does that mean? i want to tell him that means
那什麼意思呢?我要跟他講就是說
be his baby, his baby
當他的baby,他的寶貝
when done from here
從這裡做完的時候
He is also in his seventies, seventies or eighties
他也已經七十幾歲,七八十歲了
He's as ready as a spaceship
他跟太空船一樣準備
retired
被退休了
It does sound a bit sentimental.
聽起來確實是有點感傷啦
But it's also pretty
不過也是這個蠻
how to say
怎麼講
A sense of accomplishment
蠻有成就感的一種感覺
your mission has been
你的使命已經
the way to go
該走的路
The planets that should be explored have already been explored
該探的星球都已經探過了
from here to here
從這裡走到這裡
so it's an interesting story
所以這是一個很有趣的一個故事
Of course what we are going to tell today is not his story.
當然我們今天要講的不是他的故事
what we're going to talk about is this
我們要講的是這個
use him to generate electricity
用他來發電
For example, this is another new one
譬如說這個是另外一個新的啦
Mars
火星
You can use solar panels on Mars
火星你用太陽能板就好了
no no no
沒有沒有沒有
The power of solar panels is still limited
太陽能板的電還是功率還是有限
So it's this Mars rover
所以它這個Mars rover
Now it's about going to explore Mars.
現在就是說要去探測火星
then you can smooth this
那你可以順利這個
after landing
著陸以後
your cars
你的這些汽車啊
You need pretty high power for this
你需要相當高的這個功率
still want
還是要
Use this RTG, this radioactive thermoelectric, to generate electricity
用這個RTG這個放射性的熱電這個發電
So everyone can go from here
所以大家就可以從這裡啊
You can feel that this thermal power has indeed made a very important contribution
大家可以感覺到這個熱電確實有非常重要的貢獻
especially in space
尤其在太空方面
Then let's look at this thermoelectric conversion and many mathematical things
那我們之後來看這個熱電的轉換這些很多數學的東西
let's not talk too much
我們就不要講太多
But this thing has a Figure Marriage
不過這個東西有一個Figure Marriage
What do we call optimization factor
我們叫什麼優化系數
Basically it has an upstairs and a downstairs
基本上它有一個樓上跟樓下
good
好
It has an upstairs and a downstairs and multiplied by the temperature
它有一個樓上跟樓下然後乘以溫度
The bigger you go upstairs, the better
這個樓上你就越大越好
The lower the downstairs, the better
樓下就越低越好
Upstairs is the thermoelectric coefficient we just talked about
樓上就是剛剛我們講的這個熱電系數
C-back coefficient
C-back coefficient
Then there's an electrical conductivity here
然後這邊有一個電傳導度
You said that the higher the conductivity, the greater the C-back coefficient
你說電導度越高C-back coefficient越大
that's better
那個就越好
Downstairs is the heat transfer coefficient
樓下是熱傳導系數
That leads to the smaller the better
那這導致越小越好
then if you can put this to play with it
那你如果可以把這個去玩它
You can get better with this thermoelectric material
你就可以得到更好的這個熱電材料
but it's interesting
但是呢很有趣的
In the past if you came to see
過去你如果來看
This past human development
這個過去人類的發展
Seven years from the 1940s to 1960
從1940年代到1960年七年
Wow this is a little bit of progress
哇 這個有點進步
In fact
事實上呢
From 670 to 2000
從六七零一直到兩千年
this
這個
This optimization factor is always below 1
這個優化系數一直都在1以下
what's even
那甚至於呢
some people doubt that
有人會懷疑說
ah this
啊這個
Is this optimization factor
這個優化系數是不是
This maximum value
這個極大值啊
must be small 1
一定要小1
It means there is no hope
意思就是說沒有希望了
I thought everyone would
本來想大家想
if
如果
I mentioned it here
我這邊有提到
What if you want this optimization factor?
如果你要這個優化系數呢
If you want a sophomore
要大二的話
It has the scrap meat we just talked about
它就有我們剛剛講廢肉
waste meat recycling
廢肉回收啦
what else
還有什麼
our
我們的
What is the name of this one in Yangmingshan?
這個陽明山的這個叫什麼
geothermal
地熱
With this thing, a lot of energy can be recovered
用這個東西就可以回收很多能量回來
but you have to be good enough
但是呢你必須要夠好
Or
或者說
The air conditioner in your home or the one we are using now
大家家裡面或者現在我們在用的這個冷氣機
The most important thing for an air conditioner is a compressor
冷氣機最重要是一個壓縮機
that compressor
那壓縮機啊
Although the efficiency is very good, it is very efficient
效率雖然是很好電不過它效率非常的高
Then if you want to compete with the compressor
那你如果要跟壓縮機來比競爭的話
Your optimization factor should be greater than 4
你這個優化系數要大超過4
So let's see how much everyone has done so far.
那我們來看看說目前現在大家做到多少
As just mentioned, most of them are below 1
像剛剛提的大部分都在1以下
By the year 2000 or so
到了這個2000年左右
got up from the start
一開始就爬起來了
Everyone gave up
本來大家都放棄了
What is this year 2000?
那這個2000年是什麼呢
Clinton announced that
就是柯林頓宣佈說
this
這個
National Science, the nanoscience initiative
National Science,奈米科學的initiative
It's Congress passing a lot of money for the scientific community to do nanoscience.
它就是國會通過一筆大錢讓科學界去做奈米科學
After the nano science is down, the part of the material, the nano material
奈米科學下來以後,把材料的部分,把奈米材料
There are many, many improvements that make this a considerable improvement
有很多很多的進步,才讓這個有的相當的提升
However, although there has been an improvement, it is probably still below two
但是呢,雖然有提升,但是呢,大概基本上還在二以下
Especially, the real industrial application is only in this generation
尤其呢,真正工業應用啊,還是在這一代而已
If you want to exceed two, now at most you will occasionally report in the laboratory
你如果要超過二的話,現在還是最多是在實驗室裡面偶爾會報導
So, there is still a long way to go for this development
所以呢,這個要發展的路啊,還很遠
Let’s look at it again, that is to say, most of this was done in the past, because
大家再來看就是說,過去這個大部分做的,因為
So this heat conduction is getting lower and lower
所以這個熱傳導越來越低
Instead, the part of the above molecule that needs to be elevated
反而上面這個分子要提升的部分
not much improvement
沒有太大的提升
That light reduces the heat conduction
那光把這個熱傳導降低
it's not enough
其實是不夠的
how do you get in
你要怎麼樣進去
can change the material
可以去改變材料
its electronic structure
它的電子結構
Etc., etc
等等等等
there's a lot to do
有很多需要做的地方
let's not talk too much today
我們今天不要講得太
went deep
深入了
but let everyone feel
但是讓大家感覺一下
For example, we just talked about your house
譬如說我們剛剛講說你的宅子
Is this complex
到底是這個復形的
Still a regular house
還是正形的宅子
then it has different materials
那它都有不同的材料
Here is 1.0
這邊是1.0
1.0 is here
1.0在這裡
most of the material
大部分的材料
In fact, it is all lower than 1
事實上都是低於1的
there are a few
那有少數一些
can be higher than 1
是可以高於1
then here
那這裡面
At the same time, I want to tell everyone
同時要告訴大家
these materials
這些材料
You said the Bismuth Terrarium we just talked about is good
你說這個Bismuth Terrarium我們剛剛講的是不錯
It can have a good oil coefficient at very low temperature
它是很低溫就可以有不錯的油化系數
But it's only good at certain temperatures
但是它也只是在某一些溫度好
The Silicon Jomainium that was just mentioned is going to space.
剛剛講的Silicon Jomainium這個上太空的是這個
it's not very high
它不是很高
But it can go to very high temperature
但是它可以到很高的溫度
and then all behaved well
然後都表現得很好
Then your radioactive element can provide very high temperature
那你的這個放射性元素本來就可以提供很高的溫度
so just right for it
所以剛好適合它
Every material it is not omnipotent
每一個材料它不是全能
It is only in a certain temperature range
它只有在某一個溫度範圍
is the temperature at which it behaves well
是它表現的好的溫度
So it depends on what you want to use
所以看你要用的用途
if you want to cool down
你要冷卻的話
then climb down
那就往下面爬
come down
下面來走
If you want to generate electricity, go up
你如果要發電的話就往上面走
If you want to use the waste heat of the car
你如果是要在汽車的廢熱
your exhaust pipe comes out
你的排氣管出來
about 800
大概就是800
400 to 800 degrees, this one, this one
400到800度,這一塊,這一塊來著
Therefore, there may be a lot of research and development needed
所以,可以需要研究的開發的,非常非常的多
we'll see this later
那我們之後再來看這個
This thing, these parameters
這個東西啊,這幾個參數啊
it is, it's not that simple, it's interactive
它是,它不是那麼簡單,它是互相影響的
For example, this is α, this is the thermoelectric parameter, and this is
譬如說,這個是α,這個是熱電參數,是這個
When you change something, it comes down
當你改變一個東西的時候,它是降下來
But, among them, the conductivity number, the heavier it goes up
但是呢,這其中呢,這個導電數呢,越重上去
Then you are like a see-saw, this side is higher and this side is lower
那你就是像翹翹板一樣,這個這邊高,這邊就低
Come down and go, or there is a saying in Minnan dialect
下來翹去,或者這個敏南話有一句話
It's better to describe it as Yagu Zhaobi
形容得比較好叫,雅姑昭比
You, when you came to this side, this side ran away again
你這個,顧到這邊的時候,這邊又跑掉了
So, we are playing with this material, thermoelectric material
所以呢,我們在玩這個材料,熱電材料啊
The factory manager doesn't make materials as usual
廠長不是像一般做材料說
i want to see models, i don't just
我要看模特兒,我不就
Just make it bigger
你把它集大化就好了
No, your side is big
沒有 你這邊集大了
Here is a small set
這邊就集小了
so it's not easy
所以很不容易
OK
OK
that now there are many
那現在有很多
various materials
各式各樣的材料
I think I'm not going into details
我想我就不仔細講
It has a resistant rice structure
有個耐米結構的
some put some material
有一些放一些材料
will keep it in
會讓它在裡面
This we call Rethylene
這個我們叫Rethylene
let it over there
會讓它在那邊
this student
這個生
when it's hot
熱過來的時候
it will be over there
它會在那邊
vibrating inside
內部在那邊震動的
Then let the heat go down easily
然後就讓熱很不容易倒過去
There are even some materials that say
甚至有些材料是說
it looks solid though
它雖然看起來固體
But in fact it's like a liquid inside
但事實上它裡面是像液體一樣
The heat will be more difficult to pass
那熱就更不容易倒過去
blah blah blah
等等等等都有
That is the same as, for example, Nami structural materials
那跟譬如說耐米結構材料
how are you like this
你是怎麼樣的這個
Different we call Grain
不同的我們叫Grain
big or small
大的還是小的
or there is this
或者是裡面又有這個
with raisins, or with this sandwich biscuit in it
葡萄乾的,或者是裡面有這個夾心餅乾的
Various materials now
各式各樣的材料現在呢
it's all there now
那裡現在都出現了
lots to do
有很多可以玩的地方
Just now this was a trial intention
剛剛這個是試意圖
this is
這個呢,就是
What can be seen in the experimental materials
真正在實驗材料裡面可以看得到的
good
好
What about us
我們呢
what about the laboratory
實驗室呢
just mentioned
剛剛提了
This Silicon Jominium
這個Silicon Jominium
It has been proven, put it in the tire cavity and use it again
已經證明了,放在胎空裡面再用了
Eh
誒
We say carbon finer
我們說碳細者
right
對不對
carbon fine
碳細者
wash
洗
ah
啊
then pull
然後牽
that row
那一排啊
But Silicon Jominium can
但是Silicon Jominium可以
Then Silicon Tin can do it
那Silicon Tin可以吧
wash
洗
wash heel
洗跟
wash and wash
洗跟洗
These two are in the same row
這兩個同一排
The electronic structure is almost
這個電子的結構差不多
only
只是
this ratio
這個比
This washing is heavier than folding
這個洗比折還要重
The heavier the thermoelectric material, the better.
那在熱電材料裡面越重越好
the heavier the words
越重的話
Its heat transfer will be slower
它的熱傳會比較慢
so what
那所以呢
we just wanna say wow
我們就想說哇
then this will be better than this
那這個會比這個好
let's try
我們去試試看
Those who work on materials will know
搞材料的人就知道
These two things never mix
這兩個東西從來不會混在一起
you put them in one by one
你一把一放進去
as soon as the temperature drops
溫度一降下來
separate soon
馬上就分開
impossible to be an alloy
不可能成為一個合金
Then we said
那後來我們就說
Impossible to alloy it doesn't matter
不可能成合金沒有關係
then i'll let you make this
那我就讓你做成這個
We are called non-golden statues
我們叫非金像
Amorphous
Amorphous
what about Amorphous
那Amorphous會怎麼樣
then we start researching
那我們開始在研究
Recently there seems to be a sign
最近好像有一點苗頭
I can't explain it to you here.
我在這裡還沒有辦法仔細跟大家講
one direction like this
像這樣的一個方向
we are actually doing now
我們實際上是現在在做
even say
甚至於說
if these two
如果這兩個
won't mix
不會混在一起
This prisoner, I'll leave as soon as I see you
這個試囚,我看到你就馬上離開
Then can I use three, a love triangle
那我可不可以用三個,用三角戀愛一下
It's a big deal between two people, let's put the third one in
兩個人這個不約大把第三個放進來
Magnetium Silicon Tin
Magnetium Silicon Tin
It is possible, in fact this material has been used a lot in thermoelectric materials
它就有可能,事實上這個材料已經在熱電材料上面被用的很多
studied a lot
被研究的很多
Of course it's very important
那這其中當然很重要的
For example, although the material is very good
譬如說這個材料雖然很好
But you can tell when you see the material
但是搞材料一看到就知道
If you don't touch this Germanium, you better not touch it
這個Germanium如果你不要碰最好不要碰
because it's expensive
因為它很貴
It is probably more than a hundred times that of Silicon
它大概是Silicon的百倍以上
So you have a lot of money just to buy materials
所以你光買材料的錢就很多了
But you said Silicon and Tin, laundry and drama
但是你說Silicon跟Tin,洗衣跟戲
Both of these are many on the surface
這兩個都地表上很多
So it's cheap in comparison
所以它相較之下就很便宜
But the two don't touch together
但是它兩個不碰在一起
what to do
那怎麼辦
Magnetism Silicon Tin
Magnetism Silicon Tin
This is also cheap
這個也便宜
The second and third are cheaper
第二、第三都便宜
then this looks good
那這個看起來就不錯
So Japan in this regard
所以日本在這方面
great effort
下了很大的功夫
so let everyone
所以讓大家
Feel it, so what materials can you play with
感覺一下,所以有哪些材料可以玩
for example
譬如說
Germanium Terulium
Germanium Terulium
this is also a
這個也是一個
our normal one
我們的一般那個
Used in your home
你的家裡面以前用的
DVDs, CDs
DVD、CD
Once the laser is fired, it will
那個雷射一打下去,它就
in disguise
變相
So use this to remember
所以用這個來記憶
memory for CD
做CD的記憶體
already used a lot
已經用很多了
We found that it
我們發現說,它
Mainly like this battery
跟這電池主要很像
We also recently got some
我們最近也得到一些
effect, looks
效果,看起來
It's really good, although it's inside
確實是不錯,雖然說它裡面
This Germanium is quite expensive
這個Germanium是蠻貴的
Terulium is not cheap either
Terulium也不便宜
but
但是呢
from research
從研究上是
OK
OK的
ok good
ok 好
this is a
這個呢 是一個
uh just arrived
呃 才到
Professor Zhiwei Zhang from Ningtai Center
寧泰中心的張智威教授
he brought it up
他提出來了
He said you just put two, two episodes
他說你只是把兩 兩集啊
one can one hot one cold
一個能 一個熱 一個冷
It's over
這樣完了啊
uh this is not enough
呃 這個不夠
He uses three-stage
他用三級式的
Thermoelectric materials are
熱電材料 就是有
uh sorry
呃 對不起
I
我
good
好
again
再一次啊
So what about Professor Zhang Zhiwei?
所以張智威教授呢
he just
他就
does not pose a method
不pose一個方法
Say you have three temperatures
就說你有三個溫度
one
一
two, three
二、三
Then this material is very special
然後呢這個材料是很特殊的
He thinks that if this material is a material called
他認為說這個材料如果它是一個叫做
When electricity or heat is transmitted, it is called
它電或者熱在傳輸的時候是一個叫做
is one is one
是一個是一個
Belistic
Belistic
that is
就是
Not the usual diffuser
不是一般的這個擴散式的
but a bullet-like transmission
而是一個像子彈式的傳輸的話
In this way you can get
用這樣的方法可以得到
higher efficiency
更高的效率
Then it is still working hard
那這個它還繼續在努力當中
In addition
另外呢
The laboratory of Academician Wu Maokun
這個吳茂坤院士的實驗室
It uses one called Aerogel
它用的一個叫做Aerogel
Aerogel is a
Aerogel是一個
Oxide-based materials
氧化系的材料
But it is a very
不過它是一個非常
Sponge-like oxidation system
像海綿式的氧化系
Oxidizing system because it can withstand very high heat
氧化系因為它可以耐非常高的熱
so what
所以呢
it won't dissolve
它不會溶掉
For example, this is a torch and a flame
譬如說這個是一個Torch是一個火焰
It burns in this Aerogel
它燒在這個Aerogel
The L of the crab is on the bottom, and a flower is placed on it, it will not be affected
螃蟹的L就底下,上面放了一朵花,它都不會受到影響
So it conducts heat very, very low
所以它導熱非常非常的低
So Academician Wu combined this material with existing thermoelectric materials
所以吳院士就把這個材料跟現有的熱電材料把它合在一起
Then it was found that the parameters of thermoelectricity can be effectively improved
然後發現說,可以有效的提升熱電的參數
Wait, I can't introduce everything
等等,我就沒有辦法把所有的東西都介紹
This is Professor Chen Lidong in Shanghai
這個是陳立東教授在上海
One of the things he did was to say that it develops thermoelectricity. If you were a freshman in thermoelectricity before
他做的一個就是說,它的發展熱電,如果你以前熱電小一的時候
At the beginning you can only use it in space, with a very special
開始的時候你只能用在太空,用很特殊的
Slowly heat and electricity, if it reaches about 2000
慢慢熱電如果到了大概2000年左右
It has a few more, including this familiar refrigerator and more
它有一些更多的,包括這個可以熟悉式的冰箱等等
energy available
能源可以用
that's it
那到了
What about after 2020?
這個2020年以後呢
this
這個
its this gt
它的這個GT
freshman
可以大一了
even up to 1.5
甚至到了1.5
Slowly it can be used in the car
慢慢就可以用在汽車上
etc.
等等
It is more and more widely used
它的用途就越來越廣
that's like i said
那就像像我講的
if you really want to be useful
你如果真正要有用的話
Still have to go to 2.0
還是要到2.0
or 4.0
或者是4.0
is it possible to get there
那有沒有可能到那裡
Now everyone is still working hard
現在大家都還在努力
I'll make one with him
那我跟他做一個
current difficulties
目前所碰到的困難
What about the difficulty?
這個困難呢
The first is that it is not efficient enough
第一個就是它的效率不夠高
usually
一般來講
about 10%
大概都10%
10% is
10%是
already very high
已經是很高了
but
但是呢
if you come to tell
你如果來看說
If you want to generate electricity
你如果要發電的話
e.g. solar
譬如說太陽能
or wind energy
或者是風能
What about solar energy?
太陽能呢
has long been proven
已經早就被證明
He said he is now the cheapest of all energy sources
他說他現在是所有能源裡面最便宜的
That
那
We are all looking for alternative energy now
我們現在大家都要找替代能源
I can cut it right here
那我可以在這邊直斷
that is
就是說
Alternative Energy of the Future
將來的替代能源
This solar is mainstream
這個太陽能是主流
The second is wind power
第二個就是風能
What about wind power?
那個風能呢
recently
最近
Well
呃
also from
也從
The original price has been reduced to
原來的價格了一直將降到
ha
哈
and
跟
This thermal power generation
這個火力發電啊
Similar to traditional thermal power generation
跟傳統的火力發電差不多了
That
那
This thing is of course similar to the energy transformation we are doing in Taiwan.
這個東西當然跟台灣我們現在做能源轉型
Then our government is also developing these two areas
那我們的政府也是在發展這兩塊
ha
哈
Although that said
那雖然說
They are all
他們都
Very Potential Very Cheap
非常的有潛力很便宜
ha
哈
but
但是呢
The first one you have to invest in earlier
第一個你要先前投資
the second
第二個
they don't exist forever
他們不是永遠存在
And what if there is no sun in this cover transit today?
而今天這個封面過境沒有太陽怎麼辦
you will be gone
你就沒有了
Or there is no wind today
或者說今天沒有風
your wind stops
你的風能就停下來
Then you sometimes do and sometimes don't
那你這個有時候有有時候沒有
It involves the storage of electricity as an energy source
就牽涉到能源能量的電的儲存
that is becoming very very important
那個是變得非常非常的重要
There may be many colleagues here
在這可能很多同仁
all in
都在
related to this research
跟這塊的研究有關
That
那
but anyway
但是無論如何
anyway
無論如何
if this
如果這個
like germany
像德國
they from that
他們從那個
Japanese style
日本的
that tsunami
那個海嘯
three one
三一
after
之後
they suddenly
他們就突然
awakened over night said
over night就覺醒了說
Let's not go nuclear in the future
我們在將來不要走核能
Nuclear power will be abolished in a few years
幾年以後要把核能廢除
they actively go
他們積極的去
That one is these two, wind energy and solar energy
那一塊就是這兩個,風能跟太陽能
Well they confirmed today
那他們今天已經證實
Prove that this is a feasible solution
證實說這個是一個可行的一個方案
He has confirmed that step by step
他已經證實說可以一步一步的
Of course it is impossible to say within a year or two
當然不可能說一兩年之內
He can phase out this future nuclear power step by step
他可以按部就班把這個將來的核能淘汰
Even this petrochemical raw material in the future
甚至於將來的這個石化原料
Coal or oil or natural gas
煤啊或者油啊或者是這個天然氣
The whole step by step use this
整個一步一步的用這個
We call sustainable green energy
我們叫永續的綠能來
can be used in the future
將來可以用
green energy to replace
綠能來取代
That
那
but
但是呢
he needs a while
他需要一段時間
What is your government's plan?
看你政府有怎麼樣的規劃
how determined are you
你下多大的決心
but
但是呢
Such alternative energy
這樣的這個替代能源
Is it possible to use thermoelectricity?
是不是有可能用熱電呢
Thermoelectricity is far worse than it
熱電要跟它比差太多了
General Solar
一般的太陽能
you are in the lab now
你現在在實驗室
Simply more than 20%
簡單就20%以上
In the market you can buy 15%
在市面上你隨便就可以買到15%
15% complete
完了15%
Then you have to say 5% of our thermal power
那你的我們的熱電還得講5%
right it's hard how you compete
對不對 你怎麼競爭很難
so i'm going to talk to him later
所以我等一下要跟他講說
If you want to develop thermoelectricity
你如果要發展熱電的話
you want to use it for a very special purpose
你要用在很特殊的用途
Our name is Niche Application
我們叫Niche Application
What about this special purpose?
那這個特殊的用途啊
The most special thing is the spaceship
最特殊的就是太空船嘛
then it really needs it
那它確實需要啊
Only it can take on this responsibility
那只有它可以擔負起這個責任
Are there any others?
那其他還有沒有
is there any other
還有沒有其他的
Our name is Niche Application
我們叫Niche Application
talk later
等一下再談
In addition
另外呢
One is its high material cost
一個就是它的材料成本高
you say i put it...
你說我把它...
it mounts on the car
它裝在汽車上面
Then I can increase the mileage by 10%
那我可以增加這個10%的里程數
Very good, 10% is also 10%
很好啊,10%也是10%啊
if i had this when i bought it
如果我買的時候就有這個東西
Then I save 10%
那我就省了10%
but
但是呢
Current thermoelectric materials are too expensive
現在的熱電材料都太貴
so what
所以呢
Your previous investment was too high
你的先前的投資太高了
that can only be tested again
那只能再做測試
You can't really use this for people's livelihood
你沒有辦法真正用到這個民生的用途
So how to develop this material
所以怎麼樣去開發這點材料
Don't use that expensive material
不要用那個貴的材料
use cheap materials
用便宜的材料
is also an important point
也是一個重點
good
好
but
但是呢
when we talk about energy
當我們講到能源的時候
especially when it comes to alternative energy
尤其講到替代能源
many people will make some mistakes
很多人會有一些錯誤的
idea or imagination
想法或者想像
for example
譬如說
Use water as energy
用水當能源就好啊
what day is it
這是哪一天的問題
That day the dean
那天調院長
When the dean of the tune gave a speech, there was a speech that said
調院長演講的時候就有一個演講說
Why
哎
Direct water can be used as energy
用水直接用水就可以當能源了
why do we still have to buy gasoline
我們為什麼還要去買汽油
Why do we still want to develop nuclear energy
我們為什麼還要去發展核能
Why develop thermal power
為什麼還要去發展熱電
right
對不對
Can water be used as energy?
那水可以當能源嗎
can anyone answer
有沒有人可以回答
water as energy
水可以當能源
Then we can use carbon dioxide as energy
那我們就用二氧化碳當能源就好了
carbon dioxide more
二氧化碳更
our this
我們這個
it will produce this global warming
它會產生這個地球暖化
We use it as energy
我們把它當能源把它用掉
water as energy
水可以當能源
Water can be used as energy
水可以當能源是說
you put this water
你把這個水
break it down into
把它分解成
hydrogen and oxygen
氫跟氧
What about the hydrogen?
那這個氫呢
You can use fuel cells and so on
你可以用燃料電池等等
use it
拿來用
That
那
People say it is the cleanest energy
人家講說它是最乾淨的能源
because when you use
因為你在用的時候
Hydrogen turns into water again
就氫氧又變成水
So no pollution at all
所以一點污染都沒有
correct
沒有錯
but
但是呢
you have to turn water into
你要把水變成
Cyan and oxygen
青跟氧
then you have many ways
那你有很多方法
The most common method is to use electrolysis
其中最常見的方法就是用電解
our middle school
我們的中學
Even elementary school nature lessons
甚至小學的自然課
I've done it for everyone to see
就已經做給大家看了
How did that call come from?
那那個電又怎麼來
Most of the electricity still comes from
大部分的電還是從
power plant out
發電廠出來了
so
所以
not impossible
不是不可能
we say
我們說
I said before that you are generating electricity
以前我說那你在發電
What do you use electricity to electrolyze water for?
你用電去電解水幹什麼
cleanest and best
最乾淨最好了
Why are you going to electrolyze water?
你為什麼要去電解水呢
Does anyone know
有沒有人知道
disable
除能
that is
就是說
your nuclear power plant
你的核能電廠
or your many power plants
或者是你的很多電廠
you can't switch
你不可能開開關關
then you when you
那你當你
At night you still have power left
晚上的時候你還有剩餘的電
what to do
那怎麼辦
deplete its electrolyzed water
把它電解水除損起來
when you run out of power
那當你缺電的時候
when the sun doesn't have the sun
這個太陽沒有太陽的時候
You generate electricity like this
你這樣發電出來
that so
那所以
It is said that water can be used as energy
說這個水可以當能源這件事
This is only one tenth right
這個只對了十分之一
It didn't talk about how the water turns into hydrogen, right?
它沒有講說這個水怎麼變成氫嘛對不對
that's the real difficulty
那才是真正的困難
like many labs including mine
像很多實驗室包括我的實驗室
Still researching how to electrolyze water
現在還在研究說怎麼樣電解水
It is to make the efficiency of electrolysis of water higher
就是把電解水的效率做得更高
take its material
把它的材料
Because it used to be made of platinum or something.
因為以前都是用白金啊什麼的材料
reduce it
那把它減少
how much time do we have
我們還有多少時間
We were just 8.5
我們剛剛是8.5
8.5
8.5
that other thing
那另外一個東西
It would be good to say that air is the motive force of the car.
說空氣做汽車的動機就好啊
Why do you have this air everywhere
你為什麼這個空氣到處都有
You see people have taken some countries
你看人家已經拿一些國家
has proven it this bus
已經證明它這個巴士
run on air
用空氣就可以跑
And it sounds a lot like the real thing
而且聽起來也是很像真的一樣
it also proves to you
它也證明給你看
This blows air in
這個把空氣打進去
It can run dozens of kilometers in one run
它就跑了一次可以跑幾十公里
what it didn't say
它沒有講的
You compress this air into
你把這個空氣壓縮成
Look at the top ten atmospheric pressure
看是十大氣壓多少
then use that to run
然後用那個去跑
compression process
壓縮的過程
it just needs electricity
它就是要電
use motor or oil
要用馬達或者要用油
so what
所以呢
not so easy
不是那麼容易
Are electric cars the cleanest form of energy?
電動車是不是最乾淨的能源
Methods
的方法
electric cars of course
電動車當然是
You didn't emit any smoke when you went out
你出去電都沒有排任何的煙
no other waste
沒有排其他的廢物
right
對不對
But how does it get electricity
但是它的電怎麼來
electricity you if not from solar
電你如果不是從太陽能
you still have to get from the power plant
你還是要從發電廠
that power plant has its benefits
那發電廠有它的好處
Its power plant is that it is focused on you
它的發電廠就是它是集中你的
If you discharge these
你如果排出來的這些
Carbon dioxide and these waste
二氧化碳還有這些廢掉
you can immediately
你可以馬上就
If you filter it before discharging it
在排出來之前就把它過濾的話
then you can reduce the level of air pollution
那你可以減低空氣污染的程度
than say
那比起說
normal car
一般的汽車
That day the Sixth Dean spoke
那天六院長就講了
cars run around
汽車到處跑
Once it's out, you can't get it back.
那一排出去你就收不回來了
this has it
這有它的
But it's not an absolute solution
但是不是说绝对的解决的办法
Well, another one I want to give an example to tell you
好,另外一个我要给一个例子跟大家讲说
Not all energy sources are equally efficient
不是所有的能源都那么有效
For example, Hawaii, raise your hand if you haven't been to Hawaii
譬如说,夏威夷,没有去过夏威夷的举手
There are many parties in Hawaii
夏威夷有很多个党
There is a party in Hawaii called Big Island
夏威夷有一个党叫Big Island
The biggest Big Island is Hawaiian coffee
最大的那个Big Island就是夏威夷咖啡
It is produced in a place called Kona
它的一个地方叫Kona那边产来的
Hawaii has many volcanoes
夏威夷有很多火山
Monglowa is a
Monglowa是一个
Then Killer Whale next to it is still spraying every day
然后旁边Killer Whale,现在天天还在喷的
there are so many
那上面有那么多的
Natural resources, and one of the more interesting natural resources among them
天然資源,他們其中還有一個更有趣的天然資源
He is naturally the same as our Huadong and Rift Valley.
他這個天然跟我們的花東、縱谷那個一樣
That is, the seaside drop is very, very large
就是那個海邊落差非常非常大
You may have descended to a depth of hundreds of meters after going out for tens of meters
你出去可能幾十公尺就已經落降了這個上百公尺的深度
What's so good about this?
那這個有什麼好?
This genius scientist came up with the idea of ​​saying
這個有一個天才的科學家他就想出來說
He went for a measurement and found that
他去一測量發現說
This one drops 1,000 feet, about 300 meters
這個降一千英尺大概三百公尺
The water temperature is more than 20 degrees different from the water at sea level
跟海平面的水這個水溫就差了二十幾度
You have a temperature difference from the mechanics above
你有一個溫差從這力學上面
You can generate power with just a temperature difference
你一個溫差你就可以產生動力
Okay, then he's coming, and he's trying to get that one thousand feet
好,那他就來了,就想辦法把那個一千英尺
The water temperature at a depth of 300 meters
三百公尺底下的這個水溫
pump up the water
把水抽起來
like here
就像這裡一樣
wet liquid soil
把濕液土
pump up deep water
把深水的水抽上來
Then the water temperature difference from sea level is 20 degrees
然後跟海平面的水溫差20度
Then it needs this temperature difference to drive a Turban generator
那它要這個溫差推動一個Turban的發電機
It's like 20 degrees water without boiling
它就想 20度水又不會沸騰
how enough
怎麼夠
it doesn't matter
沒有關係
General power plants boil water
一般的發電廠是把水煮沸的
then go push that warrant
然後去推動那個窩輪
it if use an alcohol
它如果用一個酒精
or use something
或者用一個什麼東西的
It has a lower boiling point
就是沸點比較低的
it can do the same thing
它就可以做同樣的事情
20 degrees temperature difference can be done
20度的溫差就可以做
that's the problem
那問題就來了
you pump up the water
你把水抽上來
you need electricity
你需要電
you need energy
你需要能源
Then you have to generate electricity
然後你又要發電
After all, you generate more electricity
到底你發的電比較多
Or do you use more electricity to pump water?
還是你抽水用掉的電比較多
right
對不對
good
好
good question
好問題
Congress of the United States
美國的國會啊
divided into two
分兩次
Allocated dozens of million
撥了幾十個million
Then what
然後呢
do research for them
給他們做研究
prove
證明
he can generate electricity
他可以發電
is the electricity ratio
就是發的電比
use more electricity
用的電還要多
wow this
哇 這個
scientifically
科學上
big success
big success
success
成功
OK
OK
but i want to ask
但是我要問說
How much do you charge once
你一度電多少錢
Probably
大概是
10 times more than ours
我們這個的10倍以上
wow that
哇 那
high cost
成本高
what to do
那怎麼辦
so
所以
when we talk
當我們講說
wow what energy what energy
哇 什麼能源什麼能源
ah this
啊 這個
Where is the geothermal heat?
哪裡有地熱啊
where is the hot spring
哪裡有溫泉
first we have to ask
第一個我們要問說
your
你的
How much is the electricity you send
你發出來的電一度是多少錢
OK
OK
The second one, for example, when we talk about biomass energy
第二個譬如說我們講生質能
That sounds good
聽起來很好
right
對不對
Biomass is very good in the US and in Canada
生質能在美國在加拿大非常好
it has so many forests
它那個森林那麼的多
It has some long
它一些long就有了
But there are not many forests in Taiwan
但是台灣的森林其實不多
You get all those digital pages of Taiwan's forest
你把台灣的森林的那些數字數頁全部弄來
Not enough for Taiwan's current needs
也不夠台灣的目前的需要
then this is an example
那這個就是一個例子
scientifically successful
科學上很成功
but
但是呢
economically worthless
在經濟上是沒有價值的
then i used to
那我自己曾經
At that time with Professor Chen Jiajun
那時候跟陳嘉俊教授
There was a meeting at Air Force in the United States
有一次在美國的Air Force的開會
just flow over to see
就流過去去看
Just go and see for yourself
就好好去親自去看說到底
It's called OTEC
這叫OTEC
Ocean Thermoelectric Conversion
Ocean Thermoelectric Conversion
After the result, it was a very surprise
結果去的後非常的surprise
First
第一個
Of course they do.
他們當然這樣抽啊
power generation
發電啊
Electricity is expensive
發的電很貴啊
What to do then he just needs to find
那怎麼辦他只要找
Find a way to subsidize it, right?
找方法來補貼嘛對不對
how to subsidize
怎麼補貼呢
very funny
很有趣
After the electricity is generated, the water, yes
這個發完電以後呢這個水啊是
deep water called
很深的水叫
hawaii sound
夏威夷的聲
ocean water
海洋水
ok
ok
Then he battled
然後把他Battle
Then fly to Tokyo
然後空運去東京
Ah, it's so scary
啊 賣得嚇嚇叫
made a lot of money
賺了一大筆錢
alright
好了
It's been a few years
這過了幾年以後啊
because of that water
因為那個水
salty water man
鹹的水人
People can't drink
人家不能喝啊
So he's going to downplay him, right?
所以他要把他淡化嘛 對不對
Dilution is our general RO
淡化就是我們一般的RO嘛
reverse osmosis
逆滲透
good
好
Sell ​​after reverse osmosis
逆滲透完再去賣
after a few years
過了幾年以後呢
next to it
那旁邊啊
that pile of salt
那個鹽巴堆的一堆
a bunch of mountains
一堆山啊
Headache?
頭痛嘛
right? what should he do?
對不對 他怎麼辦
then he said
然後他說
then thought of saying
後來想到說
pack the salt
把鹽包裝起來
Air freight to Japan for sale
空運去日本賣
Raw water
生水啊
raw sea
生海
what kind of salt is this
這個什麼鹽
sold out
賣得嚇嚇叫
that's not all
那不只這樣子
when we went to see
我們那時候去看的時候
They also did an experiment
他們還做了一個實驗
Said the water pumped from here
說從這裡抽出來的水啊
to raise those seafood
去養那些海產
than this
比這個
Seafood grown from water on the sea
從海面上的水養的海產
Raised too much
養的好太多了
good
好
In the end it doesn't matter at all
最後呢這個根本不重要
really earning extra money
真正的在賺外快
That
那
You say it's a bit sarcastic
你說有點諷刺
but also
但是也
And at least he proved a lot of things, okay?
也至少他證明了很多事情好不好
good
好
we have a chance
我們有些機會
For example, this car
譬如說這輛車
Then you say you come out of the engine
那你說你從引擎出來
then to this
然後到這個
Exhaust pipe goes to this
排氣管到了這個
we need noodle drinkers or something
我們就要麵飲器還是什麼一堆的
The temperature here ranges from 700 to 800 to 600 to 500 to 400
這裡面的溫度從七八百度到六百到五百到四百
So what you need to say here is that you want to do thermoelectricity
所以這裡面所需要你說要做熱電的話
The materials you want are different
你要的材料都不一樣
mean to say
意思就是說
We still have a lot of rice bowls to eat
我們還有很多飯碗可以吃啦
can study a lot
可以很多可以研究
again now there is
再來現在已經有了
you can buy it in the market
你市面上就可以買得到
this is
這個是
Get $100 off the internet and you can buy a refrigerator
從網路上弄下100塊美金你可以買一個冰箱
what about this refrigerator
這個冰箱呢
15L
15個L
is thermoelectric
是熱電的
you may not feel
大家可能沒有感覺
What is thermal power
溫熱電是什麼好
First
第一個
If you want to put a small refrigerator in your car
你如果小冰箱要放在你的車子裡面的話
put in your suitcase too
也放在你的行李箱
too big for you
太大你裝不下
Normal compressor refrigerators are pretty big.
一般的壓縮機的冰箱都蠻大的
Because the compressor itself is not small
因為壓縮機本身就做不小
Then if you use thermoelectric
那你如果用熱電的話
that small is good
那小小的就好
You might just need a few L's for your energy
你可能只需要幾個L裝你的能源就好了
except this
除了這個之外
I don't know if anyone has the same experience as me
我不曉得有沒有人跟我一樣的經驗
you go to a meeting like this
你這樣去開會
then came to a place
然後到了一個地方
time difference
有時差
can't sleep very troublesome
睡不著很麻煩
I can finally fall asleep
好不容易可以睡著了
in that room
那個房間裡面
Every now hotel has a refrigerator inside
每一個現在旅館裡面都有一個冰箱
that refrigerator is noisy
那個冰箱吵得要死
finally got up
好不容易爬起來
Can't turn off that refrigerator
把那個冰箱關不掉
Then unplug it long ago
然後早就把它插頭給拔掉
Why is the refrigerator so noisy
為什麼冰箱太吵
But if you use this today
但是你今天如果用這個
no sound at all
一點聲音都沒有
Once we went abroad in
有一次我們出國在
somewhere
某個地方
he declared that he was
他就宣稱他是
this thermoelectric refrigerator
這個熱電的冰箱
really no sound at all
確實一點聲音都沒有
so what
所以呢
he has his special purpose
他有他的特殊的用途
or say you make a
或者說你做一個
local cooling
局部的冷卻
cooling is effective
冷卻是有效的
For example, you are
譬如說你在
when driving in a seat
坐椅開車的時候
there are some parts
有一些部分
cooling is nice
冷卻是不錯的
A
A
currently in use
目前已經在用的
For example, we used to
譬如說我們以前
There are many detectors in the laboratory
實驗室有很多detector
CCD, infrared
CCD啊紅外線的
detector
偵測器
You have to bring the temperature down
你都要把溫度降下來
Your noise will be reduced
你的這個雜訊才會降低
The cooling of this thermoelectric
這個熱電的冷卻
very effective
非常的有效
because it doesn't vibrate
因為它不會震動
So it's less noisy
所以它的雜訊會更小
In addition
另外呢
have many computers
有很多電腦
or your CPU
或者你的CPU
Your mobile phone is getting better and better
你的手機慢慢越做越來越
powerful is getting denser and denser
powerful越來越密度越高
That powerful means that it unit time
那powerful的意思就是說它單位時間
It does more and more calculations
它做的運算越來越多
Then the density is more crowded
然後密度越擠
The heat dissipated per unit time
那單位時間散出來的熱
Higher and higher
越來越高
In fact, many CPU applications
那事實上很多的CPU的應用
not limited to itself
不是限制在它本身
It's limiting its heat and there's no way to get it out
而是在限制它的熱沒有辦法排出去
Can't get away
散不了
Then if you do a local thermoelectric cooling
那你如果做一個局部的熱電的冷卻
absolutely necessary
就絕對有需要
what about this need
那這個需要呢
We can look at it from another use
我們可以從另外一個用途來看
This is what we call a hydrodynamic missile
這個是一個我們叫做行液飛彈
Tom Hawk
Tom Hawk
That Tom Hawk missile
那個Tom Hawk的飛彈
As soon as the missile flies out
飛彈一飛出去
OK you take the map
行液你把地圖
put it in its head
把它放在它的腦裡面
when it's flying
它在飛的時候
it will fly along your map
它會沿著你的地圖去飛
how does it know
那它怎麼知道
Where is it? It relies on the same GPS that everyone uses in cars.
它在哪裡 它靠的就是跟大家汽車裡面用的GPS一樣
It's just that it needs to be very precise. Besides whether the left and right will touch the mountain
只是它要非常的精密 它除了說左右要不會碰到山以外
It also needs to know the height. Usually our cars don’t count the height.
它還要知道高低 平常我們的汽車沒有再算高低的
It tells you when to turn right and how to turn left
它就跟你講說你什麼時候右轉怎麼左轉
Then when you use it, you know yourself. If you have a mobile phone, you are using GPS.
那你在用的時候你就知道你自己如果有手機你在用GPS
Your battery dies in a very short time unless you're plugged in all the time
你很短的時間你的電池就沒電了 除非你要隨時插電
Why because it's been calculating it's been following the signal received from the satellite
為什麼 因為它一直在運算 它一直在跟從衛星的信號接收到
Instead it says where is my point now
它換成說我的點現在在哪裡
The computing power is very high, so here comes
運算的功率非常的高 那就來了
If you want to guide a missile today, your power is so high
今天你如果要導引一個飛彈的話 你那麼高的功率
That computer burned up quickly so every computer
那個電腦很快就燒掉了 所以每一個電腦
Just now everyone saw that MARLO is the most profitable, and all the money it makes is this money
剛剛大家看到這個MARLO 它最賺錢 它賺的錢都是這個錢
are used on missiles
都是在飛彈上面用
OK, so you know this we call Niche application
OK,所以你就知道這個我們叫Niche application
is the special purpose, the localized cooling of the cooling
就是特殊的用途,這冷卻的局部的冷卻
In addition, I want to tell you about the many thermoelectric devices developed in South Korea called Kawashiro-style flexible
另外呢,我要跟大家講韓國發展的很多叫川代式flexible的熱電
Will it work, I don't know
會不會成功,我不知道
Then when I read it, I thought I kept
那我本來一讀到的時候我就覺得我保留了
Because you know your body temperature is 36 degrees
因為你知道你的體溫就算36度好了
Then your outside is 30 degrees or 25 degrees
那你的外面30度或是25度
This delta T is actually very small, even if it is 10 degrees
這個delta T其實很小,就算10度好了
Then you usually make this material
那你平常這個材料你要做
From your contact, the contact itself has some temperature loss
從你的接觸,這個contact本身又有一些溫度的loss
Finally, if you come to a delta T temperature difference of 5 degrees
最後你如果來一個delta T溫差這5度的話
In fact, the electricity it can generate will generate electricity, but it will generate very little electricity.
那其實它能夠產生的電,會產生電只是產生電很少
whether that will work i don't know
那會不會成功我不知道
South Korea is very very positive
韓國非常非常積極
He said I might make a
他說我可能要做一個
very small
很局部很小的
Like some Pace Makers or something
比如說有些Pace Maker啦 什麼
It would be nice to be able to make a small generator
可以做很小的發電器就好了
another one i was thinking
另外一個我在想
this is a dress
這個是一件衣服
is it possible
它有沒有可能
if you can make it flexible
如果你可以做成Flexible的話
Is it possible for
它有沒有可能讓
it's cooler inside
裡面比較涼
Then vent the heat out in the outer layer
然後把熱排在外層出來
You don't need to turn on the air conditioner so much
你不用開那麼大的冷氣
India often reaches 50 degrees
印度常常到50度
but you wear a cool dress
但是你穿一個涼的衣服
It's very comfortable inside
裡面就很舒服了
You don't have air conditioners everywhere
你不用到處都是空調
that thing
那這個東西
It's not impossible
其實並不是不可能
You have to generate electricity from your body temperature
你要從體溫去發電
i find it difficult
我覺得很難
but like i said
但是就像我講的
You have to use electricity to be smart
你要用電去智能
Reporter is okay, is doable
記者是還好,是可行的
Come again, I want to talk about this
再來呢,我要講這個東西啊
Do you know the football game of this world cup
你知道這個世界杯的足球賽
I didn't look at the chief today
今天沒有看著局長
Everyone is watching, everyone sees that
大家都看著嘛,大家看到那個
Take a few countries, and finally this Championship
拿幾個國家,最後呢這個Championship
France's Creecia, against
法國隊克勒埃西亞,對
you know the france team
你知道,法國隊啊
Finally, special thanks to Taiwan
最後特別感謝台灣
what good things did we do in taiwan
我們台灣做了什麼好事
Our jersey sweatshirt
我們的球衣排汗衫
Taiwan made sweatshirts for their players
台灣做了排汗衫,讓他們的球員
on the pitch than anything else
在球場上就比別的
It's easy to sweat
就是汗容易排出來
He especially thanked Taiwan
他特地的感謝台灣
then i mean the same
那我的意思就是說同樣的
If you take the heat out
你如果把熱也排出來
isn't that better
那不是更好嗎
You can do it anytime, it's stuffy and hot outside
你就隨時,外面很悶很熱
you feel comfortable
你覺得很舒適
it is possible
這是有可能的
so finally i say
所以最後我講說
Thermoelectric has made many great contributions in the past
熱電它過去有做很多很大的貢獻
but
但是呢
In all aspects of efficiency, you are in the niche application
效率各方面你就在Niche application
before it can be used
才可以用
Then it can't compete with solar and wind power
那它沒有辦法跟太陽能跟風力來
to compete for this generation
來競爭這個發電
How to improve the efficiency so that
那如何提升到效率讓
Even Niche application
即使是Niche application
You also want to lower the price
你也要把價錢降低
but i think that
但是我認為說
What about the future?
將來呢
local cooling
局部的冷卻
will be where the greater opportunity lies
將是比較大的機會的所在
good
好
I'm here to report to you today
我今天就跟大家報告到這裡
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
i think such a wonderful speech
我想這麼精彩的演講
everyone should have
大家應該有
quite a few questions
相當多的問題
Whether it is scientific application
不管是科學面應用面
or history
或者是歷史
i want this
我想這個
Teacher Chen has many
陳老師都有很多
Information to share with you
資料跟大家分享
So if you have any questions, you can raise your hands
所以是不是大家有問題的可以舉手
Please, can you use the front microphone
請請 妳可以用前面那個麥克風
I'm sorry I'm a layman but please advise
對不起 我是外行 但請教
Because it's on the market right now, it's about to happen
因為現在市面上 現在就是馬上也要發生
Referendum on Nuclear Oxygen Chlorine Thing
公投的以核氧氯的事情
what is your opinion
您的看法是什麼
Thanks
謝謝
This question is quite political.
這個問題蠻政治性的啦
Let's not talk about politics, okay?
不談政治性好不好
Let's not talk about politics, okay? Thank you.
不談政治性好不好 謝謝
just say he meant to say
就說他是想說
In your green energy, green energy needs to be developed
在你這個綠能 綠能要發展
i don't think anyone will object
我想沒有人會反對
The problem is green energy, as I said
那問題是綠能就像我講的
They can't be in a year or two
他們不可能在一兩年之內
even within ten years
甚至於在十年之內
Humans now include Germany
人類現在包括德國
Including California has spent a lot of effort
包括加州都花了很多的努力
investing in green energy
在投資綠能
but his your making
但是他的你的製造
It may take ten years for you to grow up
你要成長是可能要在十年
It was twenty years later that I arrived at a certain place
是二十年以後才到某一個這個
this amount
這個數量
that's okay
那說好
Then where the green energy is really developed
那在這個綠能真正發展出來的
I use nuclear power to get by
我用核能來度過
Sounds good to pass the time
度過這段時間 聽起來是不錯
Where is the problem?
那問題在哪裡呢?
The director of the tune also mentioned it that day.
那天這個調院長也有提了嘛
first nuclear waste
第一個核廢料
That nuclear waste is not a problem in many countries
那核廢料在很多國家不是問題
like india
像印度
They are also actively developing their nuclear power
他們還積極在發展他們的核能
France they have the technology to put
法國他們有技術可以把
This nuclear waste is re-enriched
這個核廢料重新濃縮
made smaller and easier to store
弄得更小 更容易儲存
but sorry
那但是對不起
We don't have that technology in Taiwan
我們台灣沒有那個技術
Is there any place in Taiwan where nuclear waste can be placed?
那台灣有沒有地方可以放核廢料
I believe that I don't need to tell you
我相信在座的都不用我講
Everyone has been arguing for a long time
大家已經吵很久了
So if the nuclear waste has nowhere to go
那如果說這個核廢料沒有去處的話
what to do then
那怎麼辦?
Everyone wants to say that it's fine to put it in someone else's house.
大家都想說放到別人家就好了啊
So it's a controversy
所以就就是一個爭議嘛
What do you say
那你說
that nuclear waste
那個核廢料
That's not something that will happen today or in the next year.
那也不是今天或者將來一年才有的事情
Then we will have been producing in the past few decades.
那過去幾十年了我們都會一直在產生啊
Right, then can you continue to store in the existing place
對不對 那你是不是可以繼續儲存在現有的地方
even said to store it in a nuclear power plant
甚至說 把儲存在核能電廠裡面
that's what we're already doing now
那就是我們現在已經在做了
Everyone should know
大家要知道
Nuclear abolition just like I said Ptonium is one of them
核廢掉剛剛像我講的Ptonium是其中之一
it is still active
它是還有活性
OK so you're not saying just throw it in a pile
OK 所以你不是說隨便把它堆在一堆就好了
This radioactive element
這個放射性元素啊
it has a
它有一個
it will keep releasing this
它會一直放出這個
These things in Alpha particle's New Chore
Alpha particle的New Chore 中之這些東西
But most importantly things like nuclear bombs
但是最重要的像核子彈之類的
It has one of the most important principles
它有一個最重要的一個原理
called a chain reaction
叫做連鎖反應
Chain reaction is called Chain reaction
連鎖反應叫Chain reaction
it means me
就是說我這個
It is OK to put the color temperature and temperature here
放色性溫溫是放在這裡是OK的
It's OK to put this here
這個放在這裡也是OK的
But it's not OK when you put the two together
但是把兩個擺在一起的時候就不OK了
because it keeps pointing out
因為它一直放中指出來
it keeps pointing out
它一直放中指出來
when you put it close
當你放在靠近的時候
its middle finger hits it
它的中指打到它
it just exploded
它就爆炸了
So you can't put a lot of lung ingredients together
所以你不能把很多的合肺料擺在一起
The Japanese one is more special
日本那個是更特殊的
That is, it has a certain amount of cooling
就是它本來有一定的冷卻
As a result, an earthquake suddenly interrupted the cooling water
結果突然間地震把這個冷卻水給中斷了
that's information
那就情報了
good
好
our lung material
我們的合肺料
the first has nowhere to go
第一個沒有地方去
the second
第二個
where our nuclear power plant can be placed
我們的核電廠可以擺的地方
almost full
也幾乎都滿了
OK
OK
So now as far as I know
所以現在我據我所知
Taipower is even considering saying
台電甚至於在考慮說
we are in winter this
我們在冬天這個
When energy demand is not so high
能電力需求沒有那麼高的時候
we deload the nuclear power plant
我們把核電廠降載
so not so much river waste
所以不會產生那麼多河廢料
Then turn it up a bit more when needed
那當需要的時候再把它開大一點
It's because there's no place for river waste
就是因為河廢料沒有地方擺
Then you say that you can build a few more houses nearby to do it.
那你說那你就在旁邊多蓋幾個房子來做就好啊
then they have what's called dry storage
那他們有所謂的乾式儲存
Now we're talking about wet storage
現在我們講的是濕式儲存
Put this river waste in some kind of water
把這個河廢料放在某一種水裡面
You said dry storage exists?
你說乾式的儲存有啊
We were going to open
我們本來說要去開啊
Is it approved by the Taipei County Government?
請問一下台北縣政府核准嗎
The Taipei County Government will never issue licenses
台北縣政府絕對不會發執照
Then you have to do it when you have a motor
那你台電機時你要去做
You can't do it with the budget
你有預算去做都做不了
Guanghe waste is enough of a headache
光河廢料就已經夠頭痛了
As for whether it is possible to happen like Che Nuobao
那至於說那是不是有可能發生像車諾寶
like the tutoring question
像輔導那個問題
That's a question of risk
那是那是一個風險的問題啦
Last time we said there was a risk, that's okay.
我們上次說有風險那沒有關係
It's a risk for me to drive
我開車也是風險啊
It's also risky for me to fly.
我搭飛機也風險啊
It's also a risk for me to take the high-speed rail.
我搭高鐵也是風險啊
risk you buy insurance
風險你買保險啊
is there anyone today
今天有沒有誰
Is there any men's insurance company that sells it?
有沒有男家保險公司賣
nuclear disaster insurance for you
核災險給你
Is it sure to make money?
有沒有 一定賺錢啊
Everyone is scared, right?
大家都很怕嘛 對不對
The insurance company must make money
這個保險公司一定賺
but i tell you
但是我跟你講
If he can sell nuclear disaster insurance today
他今天要是能賣核災險的話
he absolutely lied to you
他絕對騙你的
Because in the event of a nuclear disaster
因為一旦發生核災的時候
he can't afford it
他賠不起
right
對不對
So many things are unresolved
所以就很多事情是無解
so
所以
that's all i can say
我只能講到這裡
that political issue
那個政治的問題
This is very oriented
這個很多面向
Yes or no
是不是
over there please
那邊請
should use that mic
應該用那個麥克風
is a very
是個很
It's a source of energy worth using.
很值得去用的一個能源嘛
yes
是
But I've heard people say that I don't know
但我有聽人家講不曉得
right or wrong
對或是不對啦
He said he still wants yours
他說他還要你那個
board
板子
Then he still has his time
那他還是有他的那個時代
his deadline
他的期限嘛
take him there
拿他那裡去
thank you
請教你謝謝
solar general
太陽能一般
because he is using
因為他是用
For example C, silicon
比如說C, silicon
He has a lot of material on one surface
他是一個地表就有很多的材料
Elements
的元素
Then if after using
那如果用完以後
direct reuse
直接再利用
or just let it go back to
或者是直接讓它回到
There is actually not much pollution on the surface
地表其實不會有太多的污染
fine solar energy for people to combine
細的太陽能給人家構併的
all solar alike
所有的太陽能都一樣
You said I made this solar energy
你說我這個太陽能做出來
The efficiency is very high and the cost will be paid back in a few years
效率很高幾年就回本
but someone said
但是又有人講說
No, if you count
沒有啊你如果算
you come out of the surface
你從地表出來
And then store it until the end this solar energy
然後存化到最後這種太陽能
that cost
那個那個成本
the phone you speak
你說花的那個電
It is also very likely to be ignored by you
也是很高可能被你忽略了
He said no, but when he sold me
他說沒有啊 但是賣我的時候
Those costs are factored in
那些成本都算進去了
he said no
他說沒有
because we are all
因為啊 我們現在所有
especially in taiwan
尤其在台灣
Our store is built to sell
我們的店是被建賣的
store or gasoline
就是店或者是汽油
We don't have a detective now
我們現在沒有偵探碎嘛
is when you consider an energy source
就是你在考慮一個能源的時候
you can't talk
你不能講說
what a job i do when i go with it
我用它去的時候我做得多好工
you should consider saying
你要考慮說
when i use it to go
我用它去的時候
I generate that pollution
我產生那個污染
is there any cost
有沒有要花多少成本
right
對不對
It's the same as He Leng
像河冷也是一樣啊
wow some say it's the cheapest energy
哇 有人說它是最便宜的能源
but then
但是後來
If you remove the liquid from the river power plant
你如果把那個河電廠除液
You waste the river from the river power plant
你把河電廠的河廢掉處理
Once counted, it becomes the most expensive
一算進去以後它變成最貴的
so many things to consider
所以很多事情要考慮就是說
The process of making this solar panel
這個太陽能板在製作的過程
Its many unaccounted for costs
它的很多沒有算進去的成本
also in it
也在裡面
But I guess pollution is not an important
但是我想污染並不是一個重要的
All right
好吧
come here
來這邊
ask for advice
請教教
our land of taiwan
我們台灣的土地
not big
不大
and then add that
然後再加上說
365 days a year
一年365天
number of days in the sun
日曬的天數
For us in Taiwan
對我們台灣來講
like solar panels
好像太陽能板
seems not suitable
好像不太適合
we taiwan
我們台灣
Sun exposure is of course
日曬當然是
a very important
一個很重要的
For example, we are in Taipei
譬如說我們在台北
Follow in Kaohsiung
跟在高雄
Tainan is different
台南就不一樣
sunny
日照的
number of days
天數
That
那
Taiwan does
台灣確實
english day
英語的天
than other countries
比其他國家
come more
來得多
mean to say
意思就是說
your solar panel
你這個太陽能板
to recycle
要回收
I need money to invest
我投資一定要錢
It used to be said that it might take 15 years to recycle
以前說可能要15年才可以回收
down to the original
一直降到原來的
a fifth of the price
五分之一的價錢
Can be recycled in five years
五年就可以回收
that's good
那很好啊
then if you
那你如果
you put it on a
你把它架在一个
A place where there is not much sunlight
阳光不是很充足的地方
That might take ten years to recycle
那可能要十年才可以回收
So it's all a consideration
所以这个都是一个考量
but
但是呢
If we put these facilities
我们如果把这些设施啊
We are contracted to a company
我们是包给一家公司
It will definitely do the actuarial calculation of the cost
它绝对会做成本的精算
For example, wind power
譬如说风力发电
no one would have dared
本来没有人敢
right
对
wow you want to say
哇 你想说
this wind power
这个风力发电
One set up
一照起来一台
Hundreds of millions in one sitting
一坐就要上亿
right
对不对
then you start talking
那你就开始算说
How soon can I recycle, right?
我多久才可以回收嘛 对不对
What about especially
那尤其呢
the government is pushing
政府在推
Because you are taking pictures of this windmill on the road
因为你在路上照这个风车啊
Still have to fight a lot
还是得得到很多的抗争啊
So what our government is doing now is
所以现在我们的政府的做法就是
ok then i'll go offshore
好 那我就离岸
do it on the sea
那海面上去做
Then do it on the sea
那海面上去做啊
that cost maybe three times
那个成本可能要三倍
especially Taiwan
尤其台湾啊
past
过去
Without this deep sea construction and these technologies
沒有這個深海施工啊這些技術
But you go and see
但是呢 你去看
If you drive from the highway
你如果開車從高速公路
When it's time to stop and say
到了阻攬下去說
Hey, there are many windmills over there
欸 那邊有很多風車
But there are two windmills in the sea
但是有兩隻風車是在海裡面的
And those two windmills are
而且那兩隻風車是
A company in Taiwan called Shango
台灣的一家公司叫上尾
to put it up
去把它豎起來的
OK, originally, before that
OK 本來啊 在那個之前
Many foreign companies are afraid to enter
很多連外國的公司都不敢進來
That is, is this possible?
就是說 這個有可能嗎
There is a typhoon in Taiwan, what is it?
台灣有颱風啊 有什麼的
Uedo spent a lot of money, the cost of learning
上尾花了很多的成本 學習的成本
After building those two windmills together
把那兩隻風車一建起來的以後啊
Now everyone including Denmark, including Germany, Siemens has come in
現在各包括丹麥 包括德國 西門子都進來了
Everyone Comes to Bid for Taiwan's Wind Power
大家都來競標台灣的風力發電
So, this thing is basically a cost
那所以呢 這個東西基本是一個成本
It's the same with solar
那跟太陽能也是一樣
If the sun is strong and you have a lot of sunshine
你如果陽光很強 日照很多
Of course your cost will be reduced
當然你的成本就降低
but
但是呢
Don't worry too much, let those companies decide whether he has to come or not
不用太擔心,就交給那些公司自己去衡量說他還得來還不來
If someone is willing to invest, it is obviously worth it
那有人願意去投資,那顯然就是值得了
Of course, apart from sunlight, your unit price, the unit price of solar panels has been falling
那當然除了日照以外,你的單價,太陽能板的單價一直在往下降
Then again, all your government measures, and how long you have been ordered, actually have a relationship, okay?
再來就是說,你的所有政府的措施,你的受命多久,其實都有關係的,好不好
Can you use the microphone, others can't hear it, press it, press the green one
你可以用一下麥克風嗎,別人聽不到,按一下,按一下綠色的
OK, thank you, then the things we usually recycle, paper, can be recycled, right?
好,謝謝,那我們一般回收的東西,紙,可以回收吧
Scrap iron can be recycled, which solar panels can be recycled, can it be
費鐵可以回收,那太陽能板可以回收嗎,可以嗎
I heard it's not possible
我聽說好像不可以
Everything can be recycled, but after you recycle
所有東西都可以回收 只是你回收以後
what are you doing
你做什麼用
For example, you said that our previous
你譬如說好了 我們以前的
We call it Pai Tan Gu Xia, that canned food, what?
我們叫拍檀骨下 那罐頭啊什麼
Even the glass is recycled
連那個玻璃 都有人回收
It's good to recycle and use
回收又有用 那就很好
but for a while
但是呢 有一陣子呢
The recycling price is not high
這個回收的價錢不高了
hospital is low
醫院就低了
That is to say, have you reused it after recycling?
那就是說你回收以後有沒有再利用的
to what extent
價值到什麼程度
That thing is actually worth it
那這個東西其實也是值得
we went to develop
我們去開發的
That is, you will see game companies
就是說 你會看到遊戲公司
He specializes in recycling
他專門做回收
Then if he succeeds, you will find out that
然後他做成功的話 你會發現說
Wow, he can really turn trash into gold
哇 他把垃圾真的可以變黃金
Wow, we admire that very much
哇 那個我們就非常的佩服
because he did you know that
因為他做了 你知道那個
The best country in the world
全世界做的最好的一個國家
called Taiwan
叫做台灣
ok then do you know why
ok 那你知道為什麼嗎
Tzu Chi
慈濟
Tzu Chi volunteers
慈濟的那些志工們
especially in rural areas
尤其在鄉下地方
it's hard for you to imagine saying
你很難想像說
you know that
你知道那個
Is the political performance law
政演法是不是
There are a lot of things we don't necessarily agree on
有很多東西我們不見得同意
the meaning of the word
那個詞意的做法
But he once said that
但是他講過一句話就是說
do recycling
做回收啊
just doing meritorious deeds
就是做功德
So many volunteers
所以很多詞意的志工們
while he was doing this
他在做這件事情的時候
indeed to the whole society
確實對整個社會
make a great contribution
帶來很大很大的貢獻
what do we have to do
我們不得不得不怎麼樣
Some messages continue to say that he bullies the weak
持續有些留言說他欺負弱勢
That means
那就是說
so i say i'm not quite
所以我說我不見得完全
agree with everything he does
同意他所做的一切
but his
但是他那個
recycle this thing
回收這件事情
If it wasn't for continuing to bring up
如果不是因為持續帶起來
Taiwan does not have such a good situation
台灣沒有這麼好的現況
you know
你知道
I just came back from India two weeks ago
我前兩個禮拜剛剛從印度回來
That
那
India also has beautiful places
印度也有很漂亮的地方啊
then you say
那你說啊
a pile of garbage over there a pile of garbage
一堆垃圾那邊一堆垃圾
then don't say that
那你不要這樣講
the last time i went to india
我上一次去印度的時候
one of my own students
我自己的一個學生
read TIGP
念TIGP的
well done here
在這裡表現得很好啊
then to india
然後到印度以後
do we just live in a car
我們就是住一輛車嘛
after dinner
吃完飯
Everyone was eating in the car
本來大家在車裡面吃飯
I ate six or seven lunch boxes
吃了六七個便當
to a place
到一個地方呢
he just opened the car door
他就把車門打開
that kind of bento
那種便當就
I took a look
我看了一下
startled say
嚇一跳說
What are you doing
What are you doing
No, everyone is like this
沒有 大家都是這樣
that
那個
everyone's eco-friendly
大家的環保的
Consciousness not yet
意識還沒有
does not exist yet
還不存在
That
那
so
所以
actual contribution
實際他的貢獻
in that respect
在那一方面
I affirmed to him
我是給他肯定的
OK
好不好
come please
來 請
professor has a
教授 有一個
Can
可以
I have a question
有一個問題我請教一下
Many Koran soldiers in Taiwan
台灣很多可蘭兵
Then a mining of this Koran soldier
那這個可蘭兵的一個開採
Are you currently in
目前有沒有在
Therefore, relevant units are studying
所以相關單位在研究
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
The second question is
第二個問題是
Magma An underground vault in Yangmingshan
岩漿 陽明山的一個地下庫
The magma basement is 70,000 square kilometers
岩漿地下庫有七萬平方公里
so big
這麼大
it's lava fever
它可是岩漿熱
Is there any international institution doing research
有沒有國際機構在做研究
Thank you, the geothermal heat is what you said
謝謝 地熱嘛是不是 你講的
Not necessarily lava heat
不一定 岩漿熱
yes it is
對 就是
good
好
The first Koran soldiers
第一個 可蘭兵
Kelan soldiers, we call them
可蘭兵我們就講是叫做
First
甲
A, eh, is it the A bowl? It's not the A bowl
甲 欸 是甲碗嗎 不是甲碗
Is Kelanbing a bowl?
可蘭兵是甲碗嗎
It's a bowl, sorry
是甲碗啊 對不起
A bowl
甲碗
Of course it is because in the depths of the sea
當然它因為在海的深處
under a certain pressure
在某一種壓力之下
then the presented
然後所呈現的
These liquid cups
這些液態的甲碗
then we also have someone to go
那我們也有人去
go
去
Go get it out and show it to everyone
去把它拿出來 然後稍給大家看過
That's not it, it's like scooping up sea water
這個 那不是 就好像是把海水撈起來就
right away, isn't it?
就馬上有了 不是這樣子嗎
Well, you need to find out more carefully
那但是你再仔細去了解一下
You have to bring it up from such a deep sea
你要從那麼深的海把它帶上來
This is a great technical difficulty
這是一個技術上的很大的困難
second bowl
第二個 甲碗
we will all talk
我們都會講說
if you don't handle it well
你要是沒有把它處理好
Then let part of it go up into the air
然後讓它一部分上到空氣裡面去
The impact of Bowl A on global warming
甲碗對地球暖化的那個影響度
100 times more than carbon dioxide
是二氧化碳的100倍以上
It's the one that absorbs infrared rays
就是它對吸收紅外線的那個
Our name is Cross section, very high
我們叫Cross section 很高很高
So if it goes into the air
所以如果排到空氣裡面去
that's another question
那就是另外一個問題
Let me give you an example
那我跟大家舉一個例子
i watched a video
我看過一個影片
Even Japan, they are also interested in studying this armored soldier
就是日本他們也對研究這個甲碗兵
Of course you can think of Azhi
當然你可以想阿芝
Japanese technology they are in
日本的科技他們在
A lot has been done in all aspects
各方面都已經做了很多
Japan in order to study this foot bowl ice
日本為了研究這個腳碗冰
Later found out that doing research at sea
後來發現說在海上這樣做研究
the cost is too high
成本太高
then he ran to canada
然後他跑去加拿大
Alberta, Canada
加拿大那個亞伯斯省
on their glacier
他們那個冰河上面
Drill down on the ground to get a foot bowl of ice
在地上鑽下去就可以拿到腳碗冰
They've been doing research there for ten years
他們已經在那邊做了十幾年的研究
OK
OK
That is to say, the research on the foot bowl ice
就是說對腳碗冰的研究
I have no idea
我不知道
That is to say, take a look and say from the Japanese they
就是說你來看看說從日本人他們
spent ten years
花了十幾年
Stationed in Canada to do research here
在加拿大駐一塊地在這邊做研究
today we just say
我們今天只是說
The east coast also has foot bowl ice
東海岸也有腳碗冰
They're talking about how little work we've done
他們在講我們所花的功夫都太少
far less than others
遠不及別人
then i didn't answer your question
那我沒有回答你的問題
Is that possible?
那到底是可不可行
But at least what I'm going to say is that
但至少我要講的就是說
If you want to use it, you have to pay a considerable price to know it and study it, okay?
你要利用它,你必須要付出相當的代價去認識它,去研究它,好不好?
Then you will secondly refer to the magma in Yangmingshan, they said that I don’t know much about it
那你第二個講楊明山的那個岩漿,那個他們講我不是那麼了解
Well, if you are hot, there are people going to invest in a certain place in Yilan now
那如果你從熱,現在也有人到宜蘭的某一地方去投資嘛
It is to make clear water, and to make a geothermal power generation, which is different from the thermoelectricity I talked about.
就是做清水,做一個地熱的發電,那個跟我講的熱電不一樣
It draws out the heat to make a traditional generator
它是把熱引出來以後去做傳統式的發電機
Now some people are doing that research, so is it possible for Yang Mingshan to be better? I don’t know
那現在也有人在做那個研究,那楊明山有沒有可能更好?我不知道
OK, just to ask, there are some companies in Taiwan
好,就是請教一下,目前台灣有一些公司
Lin Jian's company
林建的公司
currently in
目前是在
Develop commercial space rockets
研發商用的太空火箭
Currently for space rockets
目前對於太空火箭的
development prospects
發展的前景
Can you analyze it
能不能分析一下
inside my speech
我的演講裡面
Although there is talk of spaceships
雖然有講到太空船
but with the rocket
但是跟火箭
two yards
是兩碼式
but as far as i know
不過我的所知是這樣
For example, explain
比如說交代
Explain that there is a professor Wu Zongxin
交代有一個吳宗信教授
I know him
我認識他
Because he's my junior on the infected team
因為他是我的感染球隊的學弟
National Taiwan University infection team
台大感染球隊
he is the one
他就是那個
the middle one
中間的那個
key person
key person
why did he do this
他為什麼要這樣做
why did he do research
他為什麼本來做研究
well done too
也做得好
why do that
為什麼去搞那個
Of course he is important
當然有他的重要性
one country
一個國家
is there a way to launch a rocket
有沒有辦法發射火箭
space
太空
this is a
這個是一個
my country did i land on the moon
我這個國家 我有沒有登陸月球
did i land on mars
我有沒有登陸火星
it's a big milestone
這是一個很大的里程碑
Of course you if the rocket can go up, like North Korea
當然你如果火箭可以升空 就像北韓
right
對不對
it went up
它升上去了
America has to be in awe of its three points
美國不得不敬畏它的三分
its nuclear bomb succeeded
它的核子彈成功了
this is amazing
這個又不得了
it's not just nuclear bombs
它不只核子彈
its clear bomb
它那個清彈
one is fission
一個是核分裂
it's nuclear fusion
它那個是核融合
That's much more powerful
那個威力大很多
it proves to you
它竟然證明給你看
so many milestones
所以很多的里程碑
then if we have a way
那我們如果有辦法
successfully launched a rocket into space
成功的發射火箭到迫太空
yes has its importance
是有它的重要性
That
那
I don't need to talk about it later, what are you going to do?
後面就不用講了 你到底要做什麼用
I will do it for peaceful purposes
我要做和平的用途
I can't tell
那我沒可以講說
I'm doing it for defense
我要做防禦的用途
I don't hit people but if someone hits me
我不打別人 但如果別人打我的話
then i think i will fight back
那我覺得會反擊
something like
之類的東西
then his story is kind of interesting
那他的故事是有點有趣的
Do you know where his funds come from?
你知道他的經費哪裡來嗎
Jiaotong University
交大
Jiaotong University is not a school
交大也不是學校
That's what they're working on launching rockets
就是他們在研究發射火箭這個
want money
要錢啊
Basically, it's all about national honor.
基本上都是國家編譽算去搞嘛
Then he is not
那他不是啊
Do you know where his money comes from?
那你知道他錢哪裡來嗎
Private fundraising, have you ever invested?
民間募資嘛 你有沒有投資過
None of us invested. How did he raise money?
我們都沒有投資 他怎麼募得到
there is a taiwanese
有一個台灣人
He went to the Soviet Union very early
他很早期就去蘇聯
to do business
去做生意
And then this 1989
然後呢 這個1989年
the end of the cold war
那個冷戰結束
the collapse of the soviet union
蘇聯解體
sell it in the country
國家中就拿去賣嘛
He used that agency to buy a bunch of oil fields
他就利用那個機構去買的一堆油田
now he has a lot of oil fields now
現在他現在有很多油田
Of course the oil fields are producing oil all the time.
那油田當然就隨時都在產油啊
So when he came back a little bit, he talked to a few people
所以他有一點回來就找幾個人說
Taiwan needs rockets
我們台灣需要火箭
Then I'll give you 100 million
那我一點給你一億
you go away with one million
你一億就走開
Then my student is like this
那我那個學弟就是這樣子
One day the boss said
有一天呢那老闆就說
I give you two benzes
我給你兩台賓士
Then you have one
那你們一人一台
Then start asking money every year to do it
然後就開始每一年都要錢去做
I admire it very much
我是很敬佩啊
that means he is meaningful
就是說他是有意義
Aren't they like box bombs, right?
他不是像做盒子彈嘛對不對
Box bombs are not always head-on
盒子彈總是不見得是正面嘛
but the rocket
但是火箭
I remember needing
我記得是需要
we should have some dreams
我們應該要有一些夢想
good
好
I think it's time to stop here
我想時間的關係我們就到這邊
Is there a problem with the network
網路有沒有問題
maybe no one is watching
可能沒有人在看吧
right
對
no problem
沒有問題
yes
好有啊
Did you prepare it yourself?
是你自己準備的嗎
good
好
Internet says
網路說
BMW installs thermoelectric system on balloon
寶馬在氣球上裝熱電系統
car car
汽車啦 汽車
He said that the electricity of these thermoelectric systems
他說把這些熱電系統的電
Save them all and when there is enough electricity
都存起來 然後電能很夠的時候
Just start the motor and that's it
就啟動馬達 那這樣子就可以
It's like making a kind of thermoelectric
等於說做成一種熱電的這個
Hybrid system
Hybrid系統
Is this better than the current one?
那這樣是不是比目前的這個
The Hybrid system is more cost-effective, which probably means this
Hybrid系統要更划算 大概是這個意思
then i think
那我想
He talks about BMW
他講說BMW
Since the ranking is very high, I just talked about 70% of the
那既然排得很 我剛剛講說70%左右的
It's all waste heat, you even need a cooler
全部排成廢熱嘛 你甚至還要一個冷卻的
This water tank is to cool it, then you said there is a way to put it
這個水箱去冷卻它嘛 那你說有辦法把它
part of the recycling, but currently
回收一部分 但目前就是
About 5% can be recycled
可以回收大概5%左右
Then you become electricity, the 5% electricity is of course
那你變成電 那這個5%的電當然是
It's better to make up less
這個不如少補嘛
You charge it, fill up your electrons
你把它充 把你的電子充飽
Or it's good for other purposes
或者是做其他的用途都很好
The only problem right now is
那唯一的問題現在目前就是
The material itself is too expensive
那個材料本身太貴了
how do we find
那我們怎麼樣去找
The element that is more abundant on the surface
那個地表比較豐富的元素
Then reduce the cost if the key player is like this
然後把成本降低 要是關鍵手這樣
I think everyone is deeply concerned about this today.
我想今天這個大家都很深切的
Realize that this energy costs money
體認到這個能源是要錢的
Energy saving also costs money
節能也是要錢的
So I
所以我
follow today's talk, I want to help our dean
follow今天的talk我想幫我們院長的
This Saturday, last Saturday
這個他禮拜六 上個禮拜六
He made a very important point, that is,
他講了一個很重要的重點就是說
To save the global warming crisis
要挽救地球的這個暖化的危機啊
There is one very important addition to all these studies
有一個非常重要 除了所有的這些研究以外
Everyone needs to adjust mentally
大家必須要有心理的調適
That means we have to slightly modify the
就是說我們必須稍微修改一下
pattern of our lives
我們的生活的模式
Like he gave a few examples
好比他舉了幾個例子嘛
it's very simple
就是很簡單的就是
Do you want to turn it up one degree
要不要調高一度
Do you want to think more about building a large and medium transportation system when you go out?
大家出門要不要多考慮做大中運輸系統
And eat more vegetables and fruits and less meat
以及多吃一些蔬菜水果少吃一些肉
Especially the beef he choked
特別是牛肉他有嗆到
Don't underestimate this
那這個大家不要小看
Because if more people do
因為如果做的人多了
Then his consumption of the whole energy
那他對於整個能源的消耗
Of course it will help a lot
當然就會有很大的幫助
So it's pretty comprehensive
所以也就是說這個是很全面的
I am also very touched today
我今天也很感動
That is to say, everyone is so concerned about energy issues.
就是說各位對能源的議題都這麼有關注
But from Mr. Chen's speech just now, we also know that
但是從剛剛陳老師的演講也知道
He is actually a very complex
他其實是一個非常複雜的
It's not that a new technology is necessarily better
並不是說一個新科技就一定是比較好
Must be because the new technology is more expensive
一定比較因為新科技比較貴
That's not something any technology can solve.
那並不是哪一個科技就可以解決
He is actually a very comprehensive question
他其實是一個很全面的問題
There are many young students here
在座有很多年輕的同學
This looks like a lot of potential
這個看起來很有潛力的
We hope that we can also invest in research in this area
我們希望也是可以投入到這一方面的研究
Our Chinese language also has many teams doing research in this area
我們中文語言也有很多團隊在做這方面的research
But he needs long-term hard work
但是他都是需要長期耕耘
Okay then again we take this opportunity to thank speaker Yan
好 那再次我們利用這個機會謝謝嚴講者
Thank you all for participating
謝謝大家來參與
Thanks
謝謝
Then our next game is this
那我們下一場的這個
The next feast of knowledge will be on November 27
下一場的知識饗宴是在11月27號
There is another theme we find
有另外一個主題我們找到
Shock-absorbing roof
分身所減震頂
Special researchers also talk about this nerve
也特別研究員來講這個神經
Then I think interested guests can
那我想有興趣的來賓可以
Or you know someone who is interested and can help us spread the word
或者是您知道誰有興趣可以幫我們宣傳一下
November 27 Thank you all thank you
11月27號 謝謝大家 謝謝
thank you all
謝謝大家